<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The English courtier, and the cūtrey gentleman: a pleasaunt and learned disputation, betweene them both: very profitable and necessarie to be read of all nobilitie and gentlemen. : VVerein is discoursed, vvhat order of lyfe, best beseemeth a gentleman, (aswell, for education, as the course of his whole life) to make him a person fytte for the publique seruice of his prince and countrey..</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1586</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 168 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 56 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B07806</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15590</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S93466</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">71305143</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 71305143</idno>
            <idno type="VID">183879</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B07806)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 183879)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2206:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The English courtier, and the cūtrey gentleman: a pleasaunt and learned disputation, betweene them both: very profitable and necessarie to be read of all nobilitie and gentlemen. : VVerein is discoursed, vvhat order of lyfe, best beseemeth a gentleman, (aswell, for education, as the course of his whole life) to make him a person fytte for the publique seruice of his prince and countrey..</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[103] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by Richard Iones: dwelling at the signe of the Rose and Crowne neere vnto Holborne Bridge.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1586..</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Another edition of the work was pub. (London,1579) under title "Cyuile and uncyuile life." which appears as the caption title of the later edition.</note>
                  <note>Title within border of printer's ornaments; text printed in black letter; initials.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England --  Social life and customs --  16th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:183879:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:183879:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:183879:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:183879:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:183879:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:183879:3"/>
            <p>THE ENGLISH Courtier, and the Cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey-gentleman:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A pleaſaunt and learned Diſputation,</hi> betweene them both: very profitable and <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie to be read of all Nobilitie</hi> and Gentlemen.</p>
            <p>VVherein is diſcourſed, vvhat order of lyfe, beſt beſeemeth a Gentleman, (aſwell, for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation, as the courſe of his whole life) to make him a perſon fytte for the publique ſeruice of his Prince and Countrey.</p>
            <p>Imprinted at London, by Richard Iones: <hi>dwelling at the ſigne</hi> of the Roſe and Crowne neere vnto Holborne Bridge, 1586.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:183879:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:183879:4"/>
            <head>To the right Honorable, Sir <hi>Francis Walſingham Knight, her Maieſties</hi> principall Secretary, and of her Highneſſe priuy <hi>Counſell:</hi> Richarde Iones <hi>Printer, wiſſheth longe life, health, and increaſe of honour.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honourable Sir,</hi> ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, a prety conceite well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayed, contenteth the minde, no leſſe then a graue &amp; great booke. In euery written worke, two thinges bee ſpecially required, <hi>Inuention,</hi> and <hi>Phraſe:</hi> The one, is the ſubstance or matter: the other, the forme or facion: but if they bee both good, they make the worke perfite, &amp; win the worker commendacion. Yea, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whiles, a ſilly Subiet ſubstantially hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, is not onely paſsable, but alſo praiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. A litle flower well ſauored is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy ſmelling: A trifling ſtone ſet hy a cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning crafteſman, deſerueth to be worne: A poore Pamphlet perfitly handled, asketh the reading. J beſeeche you then,
<pb facs="tcp:183879:5"/> giue leaue, and let mee preſent your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor with this litle Dialogue, written by a Gentlema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, rather for paſtime, then ſetled ſtuddy: and yet in my poore minde, both for wiſe conceyt and pleaſant penninge, worthy to be read. The Author therof (as a thinge vnworthy) is neither content it ſhould preſume to your preſence, nor paſse among the wiſe. Notwithſtanding, without his leaue, I make bolde to aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture the one and the other: And doo most humbly dedicate the ſame to your Honor, the rather becauſe he hath loued you long, and honoured you much. J craue ſmall praiſe for my Printing of it, and hee (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge vſed to looſe his labour) deſireth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Honours alwayes (moſt humbly) <hi>to commaund.</hi> R. Iones.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:183879:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE AVCTHOR,</hi> to the Gentlemen Readers.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lbeit I well know, that euery Gentleman, wil gentlemanly iudge of all things: yet haue I thought it no reſtraynt, but happely ſome furtherance towardes their curteous conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, moſt humbly to pray pardon if ought in this preſent Pamphlet, bee found either in very reaſon, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentinge from wiſer iudgementes, or els through di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie of humors, not fittinge with their fancies: For ſome I haue ſeene ſo paſsionate in opinion, as can not ſee or heare patiently any thinge that contenteth not their owne eye, or ſquareth not euen with the rule of their owne mindes. But, if it pleaſed them to conſider how hardly mennes opinions bee brought to concur, they would (I am ſure) ſpare them ſelues, and not with choller &amp; offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, ſo often trouble their own thoughts. Opinon and cuſtome (as daily experience teacheth) do leade euery one, be hee neuer ſo fooliſh or barbarous, to beleeue his owne countrey condicions, and ſelf con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceytes to bee beſt: and therin they that haue leaſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, do no leſſe conſtantly tary, then thoſe that vpon ſound reaſon in deede, experience, and learninge, haue firmed their iudgementes. For, do wee not finde that the ſauadge Nations, are as lothe to alter their ſoyle, as are wee that inhabite a moſt cyuill Countrey? Or do you not thinke, that many eyther through want of wil or lack of patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to learn, accompt men mad, that hold them ſelues at continuall ſtudy? And contrarywiſe, would any ciuill man bee pleaſed, to abandon his bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge, to abide amonge the ſauadge? or that would leaue the ſtudy of good letters, to take pleſure in thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:183879:6"/> toyes, which ignorant men delight in? ſurely no: and no maruaile, ſithe the wiſeſt, yea the Philſophers them ſelues, haue euen to this day diſſented in opinion. For ſome you ſe haue ſought the contemplatiue life: others commended the actiue: and many preferred pleaſure, as that which ought moſt to bee deſired. Sith then, for ſo many reaſons you finde difference in the opinions of men: and that no counſell, wit, or wil, can perſwade them to one minde: my meaning is not, that though in this Dialogue accordinge to mine owne fancie, I preferre the Towne habitacion, yet therby to finde fault with any, that either becauſe his reaſon ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwadeth, or his own minde ſo delighteth, wil driue out his dayes in the Countrey. It ſhall therfore pleaſe me, that euery man pleaſe him ſelfe, vſinge the liberty and will of his owne minde: and though it be farre diuerſe from mine, yet I know not why his opinion ſhould trouble mee, or mine offende him: ſo longe as the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of eyther, be ſtill in our owne powers. VVhat harme was it to <hi>Achilles,</hi> though <hi>Socrates</hi> refuſing al ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, put his whole felicity in vertue? And why ſhould <hi>Socrates</hi> bee offended, though aboue all thinges, <hi>Achilles</hi> deſired honour? VVhat maketh it matter, though <hi>Heraclitus,</hi> thought that nothing was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to other? Or what offence was it that <hi>Permaenides,</hi> frantickly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, all worldly things to bee but one thing? And if <hi>Zeno</hi> perſwaded him ſelfe that nothing mooued? All which opinions and errors, could nothinge diſturbe the patience of the true <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> who ſet their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in contemplation, and loue of Th'almighty. <hi>Tot capita, tot ſenſus,</hi> the Prouerbe ſayth: VVe ſee then, that the endes of mans delights bee diuerſe, and for the moſt parte contrary: although the ende of euery mans
<pb facs="tcp:183879:6"/> life, is one. The life of man may therfore be compared to Iron, which beeinge vſed, becommeth bright and ſhyning, yet at laſt worne to nothing: Or if it bee not vſed, but layde vp, doth neuertheleſſe conſume with ruſtines. Euen ſo, mans age well imployed, weareth with ſome gloſſe or brightneſſe of Fame: or if it bee without action, and obſcurely paſſed, yet doth it not continue euer: for death (certayne) is the end both of the one and the other. God graunt that euery man may lyue in the true feare of the Lorde, and the due obedience of his Prince, ſo ſhall hee eyther in Courte, Towne, or Countrey, moſt happely end his daies.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="argument">
            <pb facs="tcp:183879:7"/>
            <head>The Argument and occaſion of this Dialogue.</head>
            <p>IT happened (as ofte it doth) that diuerſe Gentlemen béeinge conuited to dyne togeathers: Among many other thinges, they chaunced to fall in ſpéeche of the Countrey and Courtly lyues, reaſoninge whyther it were better for the Gentlemen of Englande to make moſt abode in their Countrey houſes, (as our Engliſh manner is,) or els ordinaryly to inhabite the Citties and chéefe Townes, as in ſome forraine Nations is the cuſtome. Theſe Gentlemen as they were diuerſly diſpoſed and vſed, ſo were their opinions of this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter likewiſe differinge: ſome commending the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey dwelling, others preferring the Cittie habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. This matter a while ſpoken of by euery one, was at length by aſſente of the whole company diſputed by two Gentlemen, th'one (for this time) I will call <hi>Vincent,</hi> th'other <hi>Vallentine,</hi> both men of more then co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon capacity, &amp; (haply) ſumwhat learned. <hi>Vincent</hi> had béene brought vp in the Countrey: <hi>Vallentine</hi> his education and life was in Courts and Citties. Either of them with the beſt reaſons they could, maintayned their opinions, as hereafter in this diſcourſe you ſhal plainly perceaue.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:183879:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Of <hi>cyuile</hi> and <hi>vncyuile</hi> life.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>The Speakers,</hi> Vincent and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alentine.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a ſtrange matter to ſe, how</hi> menne in this age, and in this Realme of England, begin to alter their manners &amp; cuſtomes, not onely in garments, &amp; ordinary beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, (which be things of none importance:) But euen in their order of life, and conuerſation.</p>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, it is true, that ſome doo, but the moſt doo not: But wherin I pray you, do you note the cheefe chaunge, and in what ſortes of men, and whether is this alteratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, from worſe to better, or from bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to worſe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>This chaunge (wherof I meane) is like to the reſt of worldly chaunges: that is, from the better to the worſe: For as the Prouerb ſayth: <hi>Seldome coms the better.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>That Prouerbe in deed is auncient, and for the moſt part true, beeing truly applied: yet becauſe I am lothe to miſtake your meaninge, I deſire to know, whether in lamentinge of alteration, you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude
<pb facs="tcp:183879:8"/> the whole world, or ſome perticuler countrey: or whether you will haue mee to apply it to Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and to ſome ſortes of Engliſh men only: For with other Nations (I ſuppoſe) you haue practiſed litle.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>In deede, I am a home bred bird, and therfore will not take vpon mee to diſcourſe of forrayne cuſtomes, though I heare they bee bad enough: But as I tolde you at the firſt, I am ſorye to ſee Engliſhmen, ſo apte to leaue their auncient good faſhions, and fall into forrayne manners, in my poore minde, much worſe, then our owne. And becauſe our talke ſhall not bee ouer tedious, I will not at this time tell you of all faultes (wherof I wiſhe amendment:) But only of one matter, and that in one ſort of men.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>You do very wiſely to reduce matters into briefe, wherin you ſhall both eaſe your ſelfe, and helpe my memory; which is, (I confeſſe) but litle worth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>I know <hi>(Maiſter Vallentine)</hi> your memory is very good, &amp; ſo is there in you many other comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dable partes, though you, for modeſty, will not ſo ſay. For you Trauellers are full of reſpects: and in all your dooinges, your manner is to vſe modeſty.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>I thanke you Sir, for ſo ſayinge, and more I thanke you if ſuch bee in deed your opinion of mee.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>Touching mine opinion, you ſhalbe aſſured, it is, and euer ſhalbe ſuch, as I ſay: For I am (as
<pb facs="tcp:183879:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> I tolde you) a plaine man, vtterly vnacquainted with diſguiſing, and ſuperfluous ceremony, yea in troth, they are thinges much diuers, from mine e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation, and nature.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>I loue you a great deale the more, for in good faith, I am made of the ſelfe ſame mowlde. And though (deſire to know) did carry mee in youth far from home, and that into Countries, both beyond the Seas, and Mountaynes alſo, yet haue not thoſe ayres any whit, altered my loue from my na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall Countrey.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>That ſo beeinge (as vpon your worde, I will now beleeue it is) I will truſt the rather to your talke, and thinke that, what you doo anſwere to my demaundes, is in troth, that your ſelfe doth faithfully follow.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>I pray you <hi>(Maiſter Vincent)</hi> lay by theſe curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, and fal to the matter of your demaundes. For mee thinkes, (though you would be called a playne man) yet you vſe more ceremony, then I, that haue ſpente ſome parte of my life in Countries, where thoſe cuſtomes are moſt plentifull.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>Well, then I will holde you no longer in theſe complaintes, (which wordes I learne of you tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uellers.) But fall into the matter it ſelfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Indeed Sir, that is my deſire, &amp; ſith it ſeemeth, that the ſubiect of your ſpeech ſhalbe in comparing of our countrey cuſtoms, with thoſe of forrain na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions,
<pb facs="tcp:183879:9"/> I hope you will hold mee blameles, (though occaſion beeinge offered) I happen to finde faulte with ſomewhat of our owne, and commend the cuſtomes of others: which I will doo the more boldly, becauſe you tolde mee, you loued plainenes, and therfore bee content, our talke may bee free ſpeech, and without reſpect.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>On Gods name, ſo let vs proceede, and (as I promiſed) leaſt our talke ſhould extend too farre, I will neither aſke your opinion of all cuſtomes, nor of all ſortes of men: but onely deſire to be reſolued of one doubt, in one thing, which toucheth mee on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and others of my degree and condition.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>And I pray you Sir, what may that bee?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>You know the vſe and auncient cuſtome of this Realme of England was, that all Noble men and Gentlemen, (not called to attendance in our Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſeruice) did continually inhabite the countryes, continuing there, from age to age, and from Aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter, to aunceſter, a continuall houſe, and hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tallitie, which got them great loue amonge their Neighbours, releeued many poore wretches, and wrought alſo diuerſe other good effectes, as here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after I will tell you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>In deede Sir, I will not denie, that the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try ayre is holſome, to gaine the loue of neighbors is very good, and to releeue the poore is an acte of much charity: But to what end ſpeake you this, for to your well liking of theſe matters, euery man wil aſſent.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:183879:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>I wiſh to God, they would: but I ſee, that Gentlemen begin to take another courſe, &amp; fallinge from the vſe of their Aunceſtors, doo now eyther altogeather (or very much) leaue to dwell in their Country houſes, inhabitinge Citties, and great Townes, which manner of liuing, I cannot allow, Though it bee (as I heare) vſed in forraine Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryes. And becauſe you haue ſeene both faſhions, my deſire is (as a man of experience in both) you will faithfully informe mee, which of theſe orders of liuing you like beſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Ah Sir, now at length you are come to the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which (as I conceaue) is nothinge els, but that you woulde know whither it were beſt that gentlemen, ſhould inhabite (as they did aunciently) their owne houſes in the Country, or the Citties, as in many forraine nacions the cuſtome is.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>In troth, that is the ſomme and whole effecte of my demaund, and nothinge els I will for this time deſire to know your opinion of, vnleſſe occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of our ſpeech ſhall ſo require.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>For my opinion herein (thought it bee of ſmall authority) ſuch as it is I will tell you plainely, yet (as it ſeemeth by your former ſpeech) it will diſcent with yours. For as you commend the continuall habitation of the country, ſo do I vtterly diſalow therof, as a cuſtome, neither good for the common welth, neither for the gentils that do vſe it: which you ſhall perceaue playnly, if it pleaſe you to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare
<pb facs="tcp:183879:10"/> the commodities with the diſcommodities, of either: the good, with the bad, which is in either: the profit with the diſprofit, which is in either: the quiet, and diſquiet which is in either. And the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie, with the hazard that is in either: all which (without priuate Paſſion) well waied, will eaſely lead you to the troth: But firſt, becauſe you affect the country life, I pray you commend it perticuler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the beſt you may, and giue mee leaue to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber you with the diſcommodities therof, leaſt you growe ouer fatte, with feedinge vpon your owne affection. When it commeth to my lot to ſpeake of my liking, you ſhall without offence, bee as bold with mee.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>With all good will <hi>(Maiſter Vallentine,)</hi> But I pray you marke well what I ſay, and forget (duringe my diſcourſe) the perticuler loue you bare to ſome <hi>Italian</hi> or <hi>Spaniſh Lady,</hi> during your abode, on that ſide: Leaſt that priuate Paſſion doth make your likinge to their cuſtomes ſo delicate, as you loath our owne country quiet, and commoditie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Nay Sir, you ſhall not neede to doubt any ſuch parcialitie, for it is long ſithence I was there: and beſides that, my bloud is now ouer colde to kindle any ſuch fier. And therfore to our purpoſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>Then I pray you vnderſtand, that I remayne of the auncient minde of our Engliſh Gentlemen, who euer, euen to this day (or very lately) did thinke the country habitation beſt, as a life and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation moſt honeſt, moſt pleaſant, and moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:183879:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>I like the diuiſion very wel: in any wiſe, proceed in that order.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>I haue euer, and euer will accompt, that educati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp; life moſt honeſt, which is nouriſhed in iuſtice, truth, and plaine dealinge, free from fraude, and diſſimulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: things (as I thinke) litle vſed among vs plaine men of the Country: And firſt to ſpeake of education of our Children, wee acquaint them not with any crafty company: we clad them ſimply to eſchue pride: wee feede them groſely, to harden their bodies: and wee teache them Schoole lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, to know good from bad: other quallities in their childhood, wee commonly doo not giue them, as things which are either hurtful or ſuperfluous: beeing growen to riper age, wee ſende them to the Vniuerſitie, where many become ſo learned, as they gaine by learning their owne liuing: or if not, yet ſuch taſte of learninge, as they are the better. Some alſo we bring vp in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Innes of Court,</hi> where if they profite, wee ſuffer them to proceede: if not, ſpeedely reuoke them from thence, leaſt they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint themſelues to much, with the licentious cuſtomes of the Cittie: as with quarreling, dycing, dauncing, deceiuing, luſtinge, brauing, &amp; indetting. To teach them theſe, there wanteth not in euery ſtreate inſtructors ynow. Wee therfore holde it beſt, not to hazard our children abroade from our houſes, vnleſſe it bee in theſe places of order, and there alſo ſuffer them not to continue, vnleſſe wee ſee their diſpoſition to learning. To ſerue in Court, or follow the war, wee accompt thoſe liues rather
<pb facs="tcp:183879:11"/> lewde, then laudable: theſe trades are commonly hard, and their hazard greater, then wee (beeinge borne to wealth, and worſhip) will put our Babes vnto: In concluſion, our care in educatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of children is ſuch, as wee ſtudy cheefly to make them honeſt and iuſt, wiſe and welthy, obedient and aſſured. Which commodities, others that haunt the Court the Cittie, the Warre, and the world: either they want, or with great hap, or hazard they haue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Thus much I thinke ſhall ſuffice, to enforme you of our education, I thinke you partly know it, els I would ſpeake at more large: How do you allow therof tell mee playnely? And then I will ſpeake of our lyues, and how honeſtly wee liue. For that was my promiſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>I allowe of your zeale to honeſty in education, but if you mixe it with ſome other thinges, I will like it the better. That you ſtudy to bring vp your children in honeſty, which is vertue, and cheefely iuſtice (for of that vertue men bee called good) I doo not onely allow you, but commend you: Yet if you remember what <hi>Tully</hi> telleth you, (for ſure I am you haue bin a Scholler <hi>That men are not only borne to themſelues:</hi> Then will you ad ſome other vertues and knowledges to theſe, you wiſh to bee in your children, for beſides, that all men are not apt for one thinge, yet is it commendable, nay ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther neceſſary, that there bee perſons prepared for ſundry actions, not ſo much to ſerue their owne turnes, as their <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>Countrey:</hi> Reſpectes of more inportaunce, then the ſafety of any priuate Gentleman, either his perſon, his patrimony, or
<pb facs="tcp:183879:11"/> his Pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts. For as you ſaid the ſum of your intent, was to frame your childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be honeſt, &amp; iuſt: wiſe, &amp; welthy: obedient and aſſured. Al which things I allow, as lawdable, beeing not miſvnderſtood. And firſt, touching honeſty &amp; iuſtice, I accompt them as one: for indeed, an honeſt man, is a iuſt man: &amp; a iuſt man is honeſt: &amp; that is hee that liueth iuſtly &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly, in reſpect of loue to honeſty &amp; iuſtice: and not hee that is iuſt, either for feare, or for lacke of ſkil, to be worſe: for vertue is a volu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tary, &amp; knowing good habite: Therfore if your Sonne be honeſt &amp; iuſte, either for feare of puniſhment, or for ignorance, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he knoweth not how to bee vniuſt, or falſe, I aſſent not vnto you, for then, he may be rather cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a good, honeſt, iuſt foole, then an honeſt, or iuſt wiſe man: Touching the next, which are to be wiſe and welthy, to put theſe two into one, it may hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to proue that they concurre, though moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly I haue ſeene few wiſe men welthy: not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe welth ſhunneth wiſdome: but rather, becauſe wiſdome ſeldome ſeeketh after welth. Yet in your ſence (I ſuppoſe) it may ſtand well: for you accompt no man wiſe, but thoſe that bee welthy: and I doo alſo aſſent vnto you, ſo that you are contente to meane ſufficient wealth: but to ſeeke after priuate goods, omittinge all publique action, and priuate contemplation, I holde not that man wiſe, for hee ſhall do (as <hi>Marcus</hi> the <hi>Emperour</hi> ſayd of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants:) <hi>Labour and liue miſerably, to die ritch:</hi> To the thirde of your endes, wherunto the education of your children tended, which is obedience with ſafety: ſurely, for the firſt there is no nation, no,
<pb facs="tcp:183879:12"/> ſcantly the moſt barbarous, but wil commend obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, &amp; therin reſt you firme: but what you mean by ſafety I doo not ſo well know, but for ought I conceiue, it is the eſchuing of perill &amp; paynes, which beeing your intent (as it ſeemeth it is) I can by no meanes aſſent vnto you. For if you conſider wel (as mens bodies be diuerſe,) ſo are their mindes &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations diuerſe: euery one is not diſpoſed to one thing, nor to one actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; therfore whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you diſallow of alſorts of learning &amp; action, but of thoſe that be for gayne and reward, I accompt your iudgement reproouable. I wiſh therfore cleaneco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to your minde, that in reſpect of the common wealth, &amp; the ſeruice therof, (wherunto we are all bound, yea the beſt of vs all) that ſuch younge Gentilmen as are not inclined to learning, ſhould by their Parentes, bee not only ſuffered, and encouraged, but alſo to their powers enhabled, to trauaile countreyes, &amp; haunt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> warres. In which trades of life although touchinge their perſons, there bee greater perrill then in ſtudy at home: yet ſith the common weale may not wante ſuch men, and thoſe knowledges not gotten without perrill. I iudge it a leſſe euill to hazard mens bodies in them (though many periſh) then vtterly to want them, and haue our children ſafe at home. Euery man by nature is condemned to die, &amp; better it is to aduenture an honeſt death, then to continue an improfitable life: To anſwere the reſt of your ſpeech, that in warre, in Court, and Cittie, is great ſtore of euill company: Thereto I ſay there is alſo many good: Therfore good coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile of freends, &amp; honeſt diſcretion of young men, may learne them to make choiſe: Beſides that it
<pb facs="tcp:183879:12"/> is good, to know euill, not to vſe it, but to auoyd it, and for the moſt part, things are indefferent, and not perfit. Beſides vertue, there is nothing in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection good, nor beſides vice, nothing in perfection euill. Therfore though your childe muſt needes know ſome euill, in learning good, yet is it better hee know it, with ſome hazard, then want his good for feare of that hazard. If no man would approch the fier, becauſe it hath burned many a houſe, and many a heedleſſe man, alſo, that haue fallen into it, then would many a one, freeze to death: &amp; though the Sea, hath drowned many thouſands, yet no wiſdome would that ſayling ſhould bee forbidden, for (as erſt I ſayd) in euery thing excepting vertue, is commodity and diſcommodity, &amp; when the good doth or may ſurpaſſe the bad, no man doth (or at the leaſt ought) ſhun the aduenture, where good is the marke, and the end honeſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>In good faith Sir, you haue ſpoken more, then euer I did heretofore conſider: for in deede, when I bethinke mee of your diſcourſe, I reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber how diuerſely my poore children are in nature affected, ſome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues very bookiſh, others for none entiſement, or compulſion can be brought to learn, ſo as (I ſuppoſe) you ſay truly, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if I durſt hazard their perſons, &amp; ſuffer them to try their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune abroad, they might attaine to ſumwhat. And <hi>Fortune</hi> (as ſome Clerkes ſay) is very freendly to folke aduenturous.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Well, I am glad, my ſpeech hath drawen you to conſideration, of any good thing, before either vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thought of, or forgotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But I am ſure you take my mening, as it is, to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber you, &amp; not to cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:183879:13"/>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, I thanke you, that you yeeld mee that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, to ſay ſo: this proceedeth of your fauour. But I muſt confeſſe troth, that I neuer caſt my minde ſo far from home. And I therby conceiue that a common wealth, hath occaſion aſwell to imploy men expert in warre, as others learned in lawes, though of theſe wee haue moſt vſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Yea Sir, therof aſſure your ſelfe, and in ſome Countryes where God hath ſuffered vnquietnes, there is more want of good Capitaynes, then lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Doctors: yea in ſuch eſtate hath our Country beene, and may bee: for nothing is aſſured, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides Warriers, Princes haue occaſion to imploy many other Gentlemen of experience. For I can accompt vnto you ſundry honeſt quallities that are very co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendable in men, and neceſſary for the ſtate.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>Fayne would I bee enformed of all. But firſt let mee intreat you, to tell what are, or ought to bee, the cheefe profeſſions of a Gentleman?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>That can I doo, and in few wordes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>So much the better, for my memory ſhall the more eaſely beare them away, therfore without more requeſt. I pray you proceede.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>The cheefe and onely profeſſions, wherby a Gentleman ſhould receaue aduancement, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendacion, are Armes, and Learninge. For in
<pb facs="tcp:183879:13"/> theſe two onely ſhould hee exerciſe him ſelfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>Surely Sir, they ſeeme to bee noble quallities, but I thinke hard to excel in them. But is not Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry, Tillage, Graſinge, Marchandize, buying and ſelling, with ſuch other trades (as wee Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try men vſe) thinges meete for a Gentleman?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>In plaine ſpeeche I tell you, that I thinke not one of them fit for a gentlemans exerciſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>And why ſo? are they not commonly vſed of Gentlemen? and by them they doo receaue daily profit: the lawes doo allowe of them as thinges commendable. Alſo by them many poore yonger Bretheren without lande (as commonly they are all) doo by the Plough, maintayne him ſelfe, his wife and famyly.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>A poore maintenance, and a ſlow thrifte, God knoweth, and full euill it becommeth the perſon of a Gentleman to practiſe any of theſe trades.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>Then I pray you tell mee how many wayes a man, without land, may gayne his lyuinge Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manlike.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>There are three wayes to doo it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>And which are they, I pray you informe mee?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>There is <hi>Arte, Induſtry,</hi> and <hi>Seruice.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:183879:14"/>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>What you meane by euery of theſe, I pray you let mee know, for I am borne, I thanke God to ſome reuenues of mine owne, and therfore haue litle ſtudied to attaine to any thinge, ſaue that my lotte hath brought mee vnto.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>The better is your fortune, that haue by ſucceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on only, the whole fruite of all your aunceſtors tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>Euen ſo it is in deed, I thanke God &amp; them for it: But I pray you anſwere to that I aſke you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Such Artes as I wiſh a Gentleman ſholud learne, muſt be thoſe that commonly are called <hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berall Sciences.</hi> Which and how many there bee of them, you may eaſely know, yea and to what pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe they ſerue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>But tell mee, are not the lawes a ſtudy very fit for a Gentleman?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Yes ſurely, both the lawes <hi>Ciuill</hi> &amp; <hi>Common</hi> are ſtudies moſt excellent, &amp; to ſpeake breefely, all lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, that tend to action in the ſtate either <hi>Ciuill,</hi> or <hi>Martiall.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>Now you ſeeme to talke of great miſteries, but wee gentlemen in the Country, vnleſſe our ſonnes proceed in the ſtudy of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon lawes, <hi>Diuinitie,</hi> or <hi>Phiſicke,</hi> doo holde them learned ynough if they can write and read Engliſh, and congrue <hi>Latine.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:183879:14"/>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>If your ſonne wade no deeper in learning, better vntaught at all. And I am of this minde, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theſe common Schooles (wherof in <hi>England</hi> are many) that receaue all ſortes of children to bee taught, bee their Parents neuer ſo pore, and the Boyes neuer ſo vnapt, doo often times rather harme the good, becauſe there they continue ſo long, as a good mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie or occupation might haue bin learned. For as I ſay, vnles the childe be apt for learning, and his freendes reſolute in holdinge him to it, the thinge were better vnattempted.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>Now <hi>(Maiſter Vallentine,)</hi> you ſeeme to ſpeake ſtraungly, as though <hi>VVrighting, Reading,</hi> and the <hi>Lattin tongue,</hi> were nothing worth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, I do not ſo ſay, but to gaine a lyuing by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> without further learninge, I thinke it hard. And therfore poore men that put ſo many vnapte chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to the Schole, do nothing els, but offer them loſſe of time: For do you not meete many beggers that can doo all theſe, and yet you ſee their eſtate is plaine beggery?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>That is true in deede, but yet if they bee honeſt and perſonable, they are the fitter to become Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants to attend vpon a Noble or Worſhipful man.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>I am glad you haue remembred mee of ſeruing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, for hereafter I will tel you more of my minde touching them, in the meane time, theſe quallities beeing of no neceſſity, will litle amend their enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainement, and their certenty nothing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:183879:15"/>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>Well, I doo now conceaue, what learninge you thinke meete for a Gentleman, and that for poore children (vnleſſe they proceede to ſome perfection in learning) they were better vntaught: &amp; in troth to haue a good occupacion, I thinke is a ſure trade to take vnto, then bare wrighting and reading.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Touching <hi>Induſtry,</hi> I wiſh that young Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men (hauing no arte) ſhould ſundry wayes, yea, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euery wayes honeſt, try their fortune.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>And how I pray you? for of my credite (if I had no reuenues of mine owne,) I could not tell, how to gaine a groat.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Yet do not you ſee many yonger Bretheren, that euen in forraine Countryes, haue aſpired to great penſions: others haue happened vpon good Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages, others for ſome notable, and egregious act, haue attained both profit and honour, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> others for very ſloth or cowardiſe do liue at home, almoſt in beggery. Did not they better that did aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture them ſelues?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>Yes indeede, but there are few, whom fortune ſo wel fauoureth, and in attempting theſe matters many doo miſcarry.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>No doubt of that, els their reward ought not to bee ſo great, for things eaſy, without hazard, euery blockhead doth take in hand, and yet to incourage young men, aſwell in <hi>Induſtry,</hi> as <hi>Arte,</hi> I pray you
<pb facs="tcp:183879:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> conſider how fewe of infinite numbers doo prooue learned in the Vniuerſities: how few Prentices doo proue ritch Marchaunts: and how few Law Studients become Iudges: And then ſhall you finde the number of induſtrious men that thriue, is like to the reſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>If I were ſure, my Sonne ſhould attaine to that good hap you ſpeake of, (and that ſome perhaps, haue aſpired vnto.) Then could I bee content, hee ſhould hazard him ſelfe: but I finde the daungers many, &amp; the hope ſo litle, as I hold better to keepe him at home in the ſtate of a poore yonger brother, then ſee him ſeeke a good, ſo deſperate.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>The more vnwiſe you, and by ſo ſayinge you diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer the baſenes of your minde, your ſmall iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and leſſe experience: For if you had ſeene the Courtes of Princes, or the warres: you ſhal finde in euery of them, not only many young Gentlemen of your condition: But alſo many your betters, the Sonnes of <hi>Knightes, Barrons, Earles, Dukes,</hi> and <hi>Princes,</hi> &amp; many of them, as ready to hazarde their liues, for their honour &amp; Country, as the pooreſt or prowdeſt Souldier. Do you then take ſcorne that your Sonne ſhould ſubmit him ſelfe to that perrill, that theſe Princes doo aduenture? And if you conſider how many, euen of baſe name &amp; birth, through induſtry only, without arte, haue not only gayned them ſelues, goods and glory: but alſo therby haue giuen honour to all their Poſterity, I ſuppoſe you would not onely aduenture your yon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Sonne, but my young Maiſter, your heir alſo,
<pb facs="tcp:183879:16"/> yea (rather then faile) your owne perſon. For had your firſt Aunceſtors beene no more induſtrious then you ſeeme, ſurely your name and houſe, had not had that worſhip and wealth it hath. Theſe reaſons may, mee thinkes moue you to hope well of induſtry: But to confirme you, I will reſite the names of ſome few, whoſe induſtry hath not only gained them ſelues glory, but alſo their Countrey infinite good. How ſay you to <hi>Colombus,</hi> and <hi>Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putius,</hi> whoſe induſtry diſcouered the weſt part of the world: from whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> fetcheth yearely great Treaſure? Alſo what do you thinke of <hi>Magelanus,</hi> that ſayled about the world: yea to come nearer to your knowledge, do you not thinke that <hi>Maiſter Frobuſher,</hi> by his induſtry, and late trauaile, ſhall profit his Country, and honour him ſelfe? Yes ſurely, and a number of others, who though they haue not perfourmed ſo notable mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, yet haue they wonne them ſelues reputatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and meane to liue, ſome more, and ſome leſſe, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their vertue and fortune.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>In good faith, you haue ſpoken very reaſonably, I will no more bee ſo lothe to let my children goe ſeeke their aduenture. Now tell mee ſomewhat of ſeruice, for (as I remember) that was the third way to aduauncement.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>In troth, I ſo ſaide, and ſo I meane. Seruice, I ſay, hath aduaunced many, and daily doth, it can not much differ from induſtry, ſauing that it hath ſomewhat a ſtraighter rule: but deſire of honor in the couragious, and neceſſity in the poore, doth
<pb facs="tcp:183879:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> driue them to refuſe none aduenture: Thoſe yong Gentlemen therfore, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> finde them ſelues of minde capable, &amp; of body diſpoſed, I wiſh them to haunt the warre, wherin though the paines bee greate, and the perill much, yet it entertaineth the life, and in time yeeldeth honour: it is the common cuſtome of <hi>Fraunce</hi> and other Countries, that young gentil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men bee brought vp, as Pages in Court: ſo ſoone, as their Pagery is paſt, they become Souldiers in ſome Band or Garriſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, where (after knowledge and proofe) they become Officers: from Officers, Captaines of companies, and many of them go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours of Townes, <hi>Coronels,</hi> and <hi>Chieftaynes.</hi> Is not this a better courſe for younge Gentlemen then tarry at home in their Fathers or Brothers houſe, and kepe a <hi>Sparhawke,</hi> or a kennell of baw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Dogges, or that (which in mine opinion, is as bad:) <hi>Marry him ſelfe with ſome poore Mayden,</hi> and through charge of Children, become a very Farmer, or Ploughman, which thinges though they bee honeſt, and fit for ſome men, yet for a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilman vtterly vnmeete.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>I am halfe of your minde, but this Realme hath ſeldome warres, and few Garriſons, where wee ſhould reſort to learne, and leſſe meanes to employ or entertaine ſuch young men, as are apt &amp; willing to ſerue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>It is true, &amp; yet are there more occaſions to call the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to it, then they take, &amp; more meane to entertayne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, then (for ought I ſee) men of minde to deſcerne
<pb facs="tcp:183879:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> them, and were our nation ſo deſirous of honour, and their owne good, as ſome others are, there would neuer bee leſſe, then two or three hundreth young Gentlemen wandring the world abroade, &amp; ſeeking aduentures: yea, I ſuppoſe, wee Engliſh Gentlemen haue ſo heretofore vſed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matter: how could els, <hi>Iohannes Acutus,</hi> an Engliſh man haue kept that ſtir in <hi>Italy</hi> that hee did: who (as <hi>Iouius,</hi> and other Cronacleirs ſay) led 5000. Engliſh vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary Souldiers, and during the conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene <hi>Guelphi</hi> and <hi>Gibellinj,</hi> did many ſeruices &amp; exploits very memorably?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>But I pray you, are there no otherwayes for Gentlemens preferment, then the exerciſe of war?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Yes Sir, els God forbid: for I would haue no man (cheefely poore men) to accompt that the war is their occupation: But rather how to ſerue at oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, and the ſeruice done, quietly to retier them ſelues to their owne houſes, Maiſters, freends, or other induſtry, not dooing as I ſe many luſty yong Souldiers do, beg in the ſtreats, when with a litle paines they could get them ſelues a way to liue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>But what ſhall the young Gentlemen ſouldiers doo, for (I thinke you know,) they haue no handy crafte to flie vnto?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>That I know well, neither would I wiſh them to meddle with any <hi>Mecanycall</hi> manner of liuinge, as a thing vtterly vnfit for Gentlemen. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I will ſay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſith the number of thoſe ſouldiers
<pb facs="tcp:183879:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> is ſmall, in reſpect of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other multitude, they might eaſely bee (or the greater part of them) receaued in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Garriſons,</hi> and into the ſeruice of Noblemen, and others their good freendes, who knowinge them vertuous, would bee glad of their ſeruice, nay ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their company.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>In deede the number of Gentlemen, that follow the war, is nothinge, in reſpect, of the multitude: and therfore either ſeruice, their owne induſtry, freends, or fortune may, (as you ſay continually) holde them in hart, and ability to liue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Doubt you not therof, ſpecially, if they be honeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and thriftely enclined: for ſome I haue ſeene ſo careles, as they neuer forecaſt what want may fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low. But finding them ſelues plentifully applied, do ſpend as much in one yeare, as fortune &amp; frends haue gayned in many: therfore to prouide for them I meane not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>Yet one queſtion more, touchinge ſeruice: Are there not other ſeruices beſides the warre, fit for a Gentleman, wherby hee may bee maintained or happely aduaunced?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Elſe the world were harde, though the warre ought to occupy the greateſt number. For (if you forget not) I told you long ſince, that the profeſſion of a Gentlema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> might bee either <hi>Armes</hi> or <hi>Learning:</hi> wherof, if hee hath any taſte, with ſome wiſedome and experience, he may not only ſerue in the houſe and affaires of Noblemen, and Officers, but alſo
<pb facs="tcp:183879:18"/> the Prince himſelf, yet if his learning be not in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, or excellent in ſome liberal ſcience or lawes, I would wiſh hee added therunto Induſtry. In concluſion, what gentleman ſo euer hath in him ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by nature or nourture, any vertue, ſingularity, or induſtrious knowledge, cannot want place ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Martiall</hi> or <hi>Ciuill,</hi> either in his owne natiue Countrey, or els where. And though perhap you ſee many in Court euen by mere flattery, yea, ſome almoſt witleſſe, win more wealth &amp; worſhip, then many others, yet aſſure your ſelfe that vertue is the true way vnto them: &amp; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> occaſion of ſeruice doth happen, men of value &amp; vertue bee thoſe that ſhal ſtand their country in ſteede, and honor them ſelues.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>Yet tell mee I pray you, which are the meanes, to enter into the courſe and order, to bee aduaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to ſome good, either <hi>Martiall</hi> or <hi>Ciuill,</hi> as you terme them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>And that will I breefely tell you, let him that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecteth the warre, apply him ſelf to ſerue, or follow ſome Noble man, or expert Captain, that is either in continuall ſeruice Martially, or that is likely to bee vſed at occaſion, for moſt commonly wee loue thoſe, and deſire their good, whoſe ſtudies and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations bee like vnto our owne. And ſuch as fynd the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues diſpoſed to lerning, or any ciuil func<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> follow or ſerue thoſe learned or wiſe perſons, to whom the ſtate hath geuen thoſe auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities and truſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <pb facs="tcp:183879:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Truly you tell mee a way very likely, &amp; reaſonable, for at ſuch time as the laſte warre was in <hi>Fraunce,</hi> I meane at <hi>Newhauen,</hi> (where as you know who was the Generall,) I hard him commend the cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and conducte, not onely of principall Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynes, and Gentlemen, but euen of priuate Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers: yea many yeares, ſithens that time, you ſhal yet vpon ſmall occaſion heare the like at his hand, as though their dooings, and the mennes names were written in the middeſt of his memory.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Well, now I perceaue you vnderſtand me, and as this Noble man did and doth honor men of his profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſo doubt you not, but likewiſe will others. And yet to acquite your tale, I remember, I haue heard him tell more then once, of one poore Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier, who in reſcuing, or reuenginge an other En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh man, aſſayled by two <hi>Almaynes</hi> with their ſlaugh Swordes, ſlew them both with his owne hand, euen in his ſight, which both wee, and euery man muſt ſay, was a part of a couragious Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, and the General often ſpeaking therof a ſigne, hee honored his deſert, and deſired his aduaunce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>But I pray you, is this the manner of other great men, to honour thoſe that ſerue vnder them in their profeſſion? I aſke of you, becauſe you liue in Courte, where are great perſonages, both in the knowledge of Armes and learning?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Yea ſurely, though I cannot ſo perticulerly name
<pb facs="tcp:183879:19"/> the matters: yet many Gentlemen there bee ſo ſtudious and painefull, as both in <hi>Ciuill</hi> &amp; <hi>Martiall</hi> affaires are very expert, and you ſhall heare great men that can iudge, much commend them, yea to the Prince, by whoſe bounty all ſortes of vertuous men are aduaunced.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>I begin to reſt ſatiſfied, touching education: and am perſwaded, (and ſo will perſwade with other Gentlemen my freends) that they ſhall aduenture their Sonnes, more then the olde cuſtome was, ſith either by their aduenture, they ſhall liue and become vertuous, or (as wee Engliſhmen call it) of good quallities, or elſe die honeſtly in ſeekinge to make them ſelues fit for the Princes ſeruice, and their owne reputation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>I am very glad that my poore reaſons haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken good effect, but therin I wil challenge no more to my ſelfe, then I deſerue: which is, that I haue put you in minde of that you either forgot, or els for want of leyſure) neuer conſidered: For I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge you of much more wiſdome and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment then I am. Doth it pleaſe you to commaund mee any further ſeruice?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>You will neuer leaue your Ceremonies <hi>(Maiſter Vallentine,)</hi> I know you are more wiſer, and more expert then I am: but your naturall curteſy and modeſty, doth moue you to yeeld more reſpect then is due vnto mee, I thanke you for it, and loth I am to ſeme tedious, els I entreat you to hold your promiſe: that is, to heare mee tell of our countrey
<pb facs="tcp:183879:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> commodities &amp; the content wherin we liue there: For though I now yeelde, that the education of Gentlemen is beſt abroad, yet mee thinkes their continuall habitation ſhould bee beſt in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try at home.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>I hope you will not euer dwell in that opinion: but I pray you begin to tell of your Countrey de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightes, and what is your manner of liuinge. I will with all my hart, both paciently heare you, and boldly (as you gaue leaue) tell you my minde, how I allow of your reaſons.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>I ſay then, that our Country habitacion is more godly, more honorable, more holeſome, more quiet, more pleaſant, and profitable, then it can be in any Cittie or Burrough.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Surely Sir, you haue ſpoken of great reſpects, why you ſhould loue the Country dwellinge, and though I will beleue that the thing is (as you ſay) yet ſith wee are in diſpute of the matter, you muſt giue mee leaue to demaund either reaſons or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtracions, why indeed it is ſo?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>I will proceede, as orderly as I can, and make proofe (as I hope) of all my ſpeeche, &amp; firſt becauſe I alleadged, that our Country liues, (I ſpeake without compariſon) was more godly, then the life of the Cittie: That opinion I conceaue, becauſe I finde there, much loue &amp; charity, which as I take it, are two ſpeciall markes of godlines, and ſeldom found in Citties, where euery man almoſt, lyueth
<pb facs="tcp:183879:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> to him ſelfe: For wheras Neighbours doo meete often without ceremony, chearing, and conuerſing one with an other, without diſdayne, or enuie, (as wee do in the Countrey,) there I iudge is loue, and good neighbourhood: Likewiſe where hoſpitali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is liberally kept, and many Children and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes daily fed, with all other commers: there (as I alſo thinke) is much charitie: in the Towne it ſeemeth the contrary, there is no meetinge of neighbours, without ſpecial conuitation, no ſaluta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, without much reſpect, &amp; ceremony, no number of Seruaunts, but thoſe that for neceſſary vſes are imployable. So as in breefe, there ſeemeth to bee litle loue amonge equals, and leſſe liberali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to inferiours: Wherupon I inferre, that in Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Townes, is leſſe plenty of both theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties: (I meane loue and charity,) then is with vs in the Country. How ſay you <hi>(M. Vallentine,)</hi> haue I ſpoken well or no?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>You ſpeake euer exceeding well, yet I pray you with patience, heare what may be ſayd to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. It ſeemeth that ceremonies of ciuility, doth make you doubt of loue among town inhabitants, and ſo conſequently there wanteth ſome parte of that godly good will you finde, or imagine to be in the Country. Truely Sir, if you were aſwell ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted in any Cittie, as you are in the Shier, where you abide: you ſhould finde the ſame affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion among men, that there are, ſome more &amp; ſome leſſe of acquaintance and freendſhip amongſt theſe men, as they bee more or leſſe a kinne, allied, or of
<pb facs="tcp:183879:20"/> conformitie, or diſformitie in diſpoſition. For there are few men ſo vniuerſally curteous or kinde, as make accompt of all men alike (which ſo beeinge) bringeth mee to beleeue, that when good freends are diſpoſed to meete, it is better to bee eyther in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uited, or occaſioned, then (as they doo in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey) hand ouerhead reſort to a gentlemans houſe, where (becauſe the Maiſter doth not make choice of his gueſtes, ſometimes very ſtraungers do there meete, yea, other whiles meare enemyes, which (as you can conceaue) muſt needes marre all the myrth. And if any of theſe gueſtes doo happen to receaue leſſe curteſy, or entertainment then the other, hee falleth forthwith into offence or ielouſy agaynſt the Maiſter of the houſe, and holde him more then halfe his foe. Which diſpleaſure could not happen, if no man would reſorte thither vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden: Beſides that, (if you marke it well) when a knot of good and famylier freendes bee met, to make merry, and talke, (as true freendes often doo) merrilly, and liberally: if but one extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary man (none of this troupe) doth hap to come in) you ſhall finde all the mirth marred, and their free ſpeeche conuerted to reſpecte, yea, (ſhall I tell all) that gueſte vnlooked for, maketh one to many: for the number of lodginges. And ſo the Maiſter of the houſe, is driuen eyther to forſake his owne bead, or diſcharge his vnbiden gueſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>It is true that you ſay, that theſe vnacquainted gueſtes do occaſion, alteration of cheare, and I my ſelfe in my poore houſe, haue diuerſe times beene
<pb facs="tcp:183879:21"/> ſo haunted with gueſts, as I was driuen out of mine owne bed, to lye at ſome Tennants houſe of mine, for a night or two: Notwithſtanding, I toke it for no great trouble, ſo long as my freends found themſelues content and welcome.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>But Sir, are you ſure they were all your freendes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>Yea ſurely, I ſo thinke, though ſome of them I had neuer ſeene before that day.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Doo you not thinke you haue as true freendes as any of theſe haunt feaſtes, that dwell far from you, or that do viſite you at their occaſions, or your owne conuitation?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>Yes truly, and my trouble the leſſe, if wee were leſſe haunted, but the Country cuſtome is, to bid euery man welcome, and the more reſort he hath, the more is the Maiſter of the houſe honored, and the more authority a Gentleman hath in the ſhier, the more is the reſort vnto him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Verely, I ſo thinke, for as his true freends do ſeeke him for loue and honour, ſo are there others that do it for flattery or feare: Thus you ſee how eaſely you may bee deceaued in the loue of your Neighboures, and that haunting your houſe, may bee for other cauſe or occaſion, aſwell as loue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, it may ſo bee right well, but yet you can ſay litle agaynſt mee, touching our liberalitie and
<pb facs="tcp:183879:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> charity, which wee vſe in the Country, keepinge our gates open for all men, and feeding many tall fellowes to attend vpon vs: alſo relyuing all Beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, that aſke at our gates, with money, meat, or bothe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>I am loth to ſpeak againſt theſe cuſtomes, becauſe they are the cheefe commendacions of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey: and yet, ſith I haue already my pardon and lycence to ſay what I luſt, againſt you, let mee aſke what ſortes of men, doo enter commonly within your gates, which (as you ſay) are neuer ſhut?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>There doo reſort vnto vs of all ſortes, I meane Noble men, Gentlemen, Yeomen, our Neighbors, &amp; many others, that either haue occaſion to come thither for buſines, or paſſe that way for their own affaires or pleaſures.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Theſe mennes preſence in your houſes, do rather honor you, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhew that therby you be charitable. But what bee theſe tall fellowes of whom you ſpeake?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>They bee our ſeruingmen, that attend vpon our Table, and follow vs in the ſtreetes, when wee bee at <hi>London,</hi> or any other great Towne, and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh our Halles at home.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>But I pray you, haue they no other quallities, wherin to ſerue you, or doo you vſe them, for no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther purpoſe, then attend on your Table, or follow you as ſhadowes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:183879:22"/>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>Surely no, neither is it the manner to offer them any labour or drudgery, for therof they would take great ſcorne, beeing cumly perſonages, &amp; common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the ſonnes of ſome honeſt Yeomen, or Farmers of the Countrey.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Then can I compare them to <hi>Monckes,</hi> and fat <hi>Friers,</hi> who vnder pretence of prayer, wanne them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues a laſie life, and liued vpon others laboure: So theſe men, beeing called men of ſeruice, do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſſe then ſerue: I doo not therfore accompte you charitable in feeding of ſuch idle folke: for that is ſayd to bee ſpent, or geuen charitably, which is beſtowed on beggers, the blinde, and lame, and ſuch like: but not on theſe ſturdy fellowes, &amp; need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les ſeruauntes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>Doo you ſo ſay Sir? were it for the worſhip of a Gentleman, hauing good lande and reuenues to keepe no more ſeruaunts, then (as they doo in Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties) thoſe that for their neceſſary vſes they muſt needes imploy? If wee Gentlemen ſhould ſo doo, how ſhould wee furniſh our Halles? how ſhould wee bee ready for quarrellers? or how ſhould our Wiues bee wayted on when they ride a broade, as commonly their cuſtome is, cheefely in Sommer, the faire ſeaſon and hunting time?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>In good ſooth, you haue now ſayd much, but no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to purpoſe, for though it hath been a cuſtome to keepe theſe needleſſe men, yet the cuſtome being not good, or not profitable, it ought to be baniſhed.
<pb facs="tcp:183879:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
                  <hi>Among the lubberly Monckes, and fat headed Friers,</hi> your Halles will beſt ſhew their good proportion, when they be not ouer ful: your quarrels would be perfourmed, with your owne perſons, and your wiues (beeinge well vſed) ſhould bee no common huntreſſe, nor gadders abroade, though I deeme not, ſuch hath bin the vſe that Ladies, and gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>women, (euen in their Huſbandes abſence) ſhould ride a hawking, or huntinge.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>If this cuſtome of keeping great numbers of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uingmen had not beene good, and commendable, how happeneth it, that neither lawes hath forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den it, nor experience hath not diſprooued it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>I will tell you how (in mine opinion,) this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berſome and vnprofitable cuſtome came, which in deede (as I thinke) at the firſt was very neceſſary, but now cleane contrary.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>How can a thing bee good once, and after proue euill, cheefely a cuſtome ſo long vſed?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Yes ſurely Sir, and you ſee many lawes or ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes made with good conſent, and vpon iuſt occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which afterwardes become either ſo vnprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, or ſo ſeuere, as by like conſent they be annul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, as you your ſelf, (euen in your owne age) might haue marked: Likewiſe would cuſtomes which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come vnprofitable, or vnfit for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon welth be v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. And touching our matter of many idle ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts I thinke, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> at ſuch time, as this Realm was deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into ſundry principalities, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> therby co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuall
<pb facs="tcp:183879:23"/> quarrel and diſcord grew among the Princes, and their ſundry ſubiectes of neceſſity the Noble men, and Gentlemen were forced to keepe the greateſt number of Seruauntes they were able: Not for the purpoſes you alleadge, but rather (as a Gard) to defend them from the fury of their enemies: ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther els this cuſtome began in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time of the great ciuill warres, which continued many yeares, and was (as you know) called the <hi>Barrons</hi> warre. In theſe times, it was not onely not folly, but rather great wiſedome to haue numbers of ſeruauntes, and followers, though with charge, to attend vpon Gentlemen for their defence: but had they liued in continuall quiet, free from ciuill diſcention, I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, they would not haue continued thoſe Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons for their vayne glory, or their ſenceles ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, (as I may call it.)</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>In good earneſt, you ſpeake reaſonably.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Yea Sir, I can bringe one other matter to your mind, wherof you may rather gather, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Realme, hath been in times heretofore great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly trauelled, and the Nobillity in much perrill: for if you conſider wel the ſights, &amp; manner of their moſt auncient houſes, you ſhall finde they were all (for the moſt part) either Caſtelles or houſes trenched, or Moted about: as buildinges, made rather for defence, then other reſpect, either of pleſure or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite. Wherfore ſeeinge they did chooſe an habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for ſtrength and defence, it is very like they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo accompanied them ſelues, as ſtrongly as they were able. And I dare warrant you that in thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:183879:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> dayes, though they did (as wee do) entertaine ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſeruaunts, yet was their conſideration diuerſe from ours. For as wee regarde cheefely the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines of the perſon, ſo did they ſtudy to take them that were expert in the warre, and weapon of that age: as Pikes, Bowes, Swordes, and ſheeldes (for ſhot, I geſſe, they vſed not:) Alſo they made choice (as I likewiſe ſuppoſe) of men that were hardy and ſtrong, becauſe, (hauinge litle, or no vſe of Artillary or ſmall ſhot,) the cheefe ſeruice con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted vpon force: both in defence of their Caſtels or houſes, and alſo in the feelde fight.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>All this while (I confeſſe) you reaſon very proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly: but now (thankes to god, and good gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) wee haue no neede, as they had, and yet haue we as good reuenues or more then the noble or Gentlemen of thoſe ages, and enioy them more quietly: why ſhould wee not then keepe them ſtill, to attend vpon vs for our honour &amp; worſhip? And they are not altogeather ſo vnquallified, or idle, as you are perſwaded.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Then I pray you, enforme mee further of their vertues or quallities, ſith I haue plainely tolde you, for what cauſe the cuſtome of Seruingmen began, and of what condicion they were.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>Among our Yeomen, you ſhal finde ſome (yea very many) wel brought vp, and expert in ſundry ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and neceſſary knowledges, without which they cannot (as they doo) ſerue a noble man, or gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man: and not to holde you in longer expectation
<pb facs="tcp:183879:24" rendition="simple:additions"/> what they are. You ſhall know that our ſeruing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, beſides that they al, (or the greateſt number) can well and decently weare their garments, and cheefely their lyuery coates, their ſwordes &amp; buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, they can alſo carue very cumly at your table, as to vnlaſe a Conny, to raiſe a Capon, trompe a Crane, and ſo likewiſe handle all other diſhes, and meates that are ſet on the board before you: ſome of them alſo can wreſtle, leape well, run &amp; daunce. There are alſo of thoſe, that can ſhoote in longe Bowes, croſſe Bowes, or handgunne: Yea there wanteth not ſome that are both ſo wiſe, and of ſo good audacitie, as they can, and doo (for lacke of better company) entertaine their Maiſter with table talke, bee it is pleaſure to ſpeake either of Hawkes, or houndes, fiſhinge, or fowling, ſowing or graffinge, ditchinge or hedginge, the dearth or cheapenes of grayne, or any ſuch matters, wherof Gentlemen commonly ſpeake in the Country: bee it either of pleaſure or profit, theſe good fellowes know ſumwhat in all.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Verely ſyr, you haue told mee newes, I would faine know more of theſe men, and of their feates, I will no more ſay vertues, for that ſmels to much of beyond ſeas.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>If you knew, what honour or worſhip theſe can doo, to a Noble man in his Countrey houſe, you would rather giue a good ſeruingman fortie pounds wages, then want his ſeruice ſome one day: I meane, eyther when you haue ſtore of ſtraungers (for ſo wee call our gueſtes,) or els
<pb facs="tcp:183879:24" rendition="simple:additions"/> when you are from home: For in your abſence, hee cannot onely ſee thinges in good order, but alſo entertayne them, firſt in the Hall, nexte in your Parlour, (or if you keepe that manner or eſtate) in your great Chamber, as a right good Gentleman, and ſome times a Lorde, may bee content (in their Maiſters abſence) to take all in good part: Yea to tell you all, ſome heires, (I ſpeake playnely in this place) bee ſo ſimple, as their ſeruingmen, by their counſell, in prouidinge, foreſeeinge, entertaininge and ſparinge, doo maintayne theyr honours and worſhips.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>You ſpeake well, for theſe ſortes of ſeruauntes, I luſt not yet a while to reply, I pray you ſay on. Are theſe all, that his folly, &amp; fooliſh ambition doth entertaine? you muſt not tell what I ſay.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>I am ſure you ſpeake merrily: but yet I will proceede, theſe ſortes of men bee the moſt number: But beſides them wee haue Subſeruingmen, (as I may call them,) ſeldome in ſight: As Bakers, Brewers, Chamberlaines, Wardrobers, Faulke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, Hunters, Horſekeepers, Lackeies: and (for the moſt parte) a naturall Foole, or Ieſter to make vs ſporte: Alſo a Cooke, with a Scullin or two, Launderers, Hynes, and Hogheards, with ſome other ſilly ſlaues, as I know not how to name them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>I thought I had knowen all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> retinue, of a Noble mans, or Gent. houſe. But now I finde, I do not, for it ſemeth a whole Army or Camp: and yet, ſhal
<pb facs="tcp:183879:25"/> I tell you truely what I thinke) this laſt number though it bee leaſt, is the more neceſſary ſorte of ſeruaunts, becauſe theſe ſerue neceſſity, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuperfluity, or (I may call it) ambition: But altogeather they make a world: For my parte, I had rather haue a litle with quiet, then a great deale with ſuch confuſion: for though money and prouiſion bee plentifull in the Countrey, yet ſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and eating, deuoureth all: and for ought I conceaue, there is no great charity in feedinge of many of theſe men, who eate much, and get litle.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>I muſt confeſſe it true, that our charge is great, and ſome of them are alſo prowde, and euill natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red people, as were it not for their Parents ſakes (who bee our good freendes, or Tennants) wee would many times diſcharge our houſes of them: But partly for thoſe reſpects, and partly for feare, beeing out of ſeruice, they ſhould fall into offence of law, wee kepe them, though to our great charge and diſcontent: for well you know, it were great pittie to ſee a tall fellow to clyme a Gibbet.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Euen ſo it were in deed: and yet, if you hap to haue in your ground a fayre great Tree, that yeelds you no fruit: but with the bowes therof, ouer droppeth an Aker of graſſe, which therby (I meane for want of ſunne ſhine) cannot proſper: were it not better to hew downe this tree, then for the onely beauty therof, ſuffer it to grow to your continuall loſſe and hinderance?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>Yes mary would I, but to what purpoſe would
<pb facs="tcp:183879:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> you apply this Parrable?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>I can compare a cumly vnquallified ſeruaunt to this Tree, for if hee can none other good, but ſhew forth his proper perſon, nor intendeth to bee more profitable, it maketh no great matter, what becommeth of him: cheefely, if hee bee vnhoneſt, and of euil condicion. Let not that therfore comber your conſcience: but a gods name prefer your profit beefore the releefe or maintenaunce of ſuch ydle folke.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>In very deed ſyr, I haue heard of learned Clerks, that God and nature hath made nothing in vaine: wherupo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I iudge, that men who can no good, the fault is rather their owne, then natures: yet doth it ſumwhat ſtay in my ſtomack, to diſcharge a luſty fellow, though his conditions bee but ſkantly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable. And the reaſon is becauſe hee becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth a houſe well.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>If that bee all, that bindeth you to your charge, I will tell you how you ſhall better cheape furniſh your houſe, then of theſe perſons, of whom you haue no other vſe, then to looke on them, becauſe they are cumly.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>As how, I pray you? for conſidering the ſmal ſeruice they doo, and yet are men healthy &amp; ſound, I ſuppoſe it is no great charity to keepe them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>What I meane to tell you, is this: that you were beſt to cauſe al their pictures to be drawen in their
<pb facs="tcp:183879:26"/> beſt array, and hange them vp in your Hall, and you ſhall finde them as ſeemely furniture, as the men them ſelues, and yet they will put you to no coſt, eyther in meate, money, or cloth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>You ſpeake merrily, but yet in good faith rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably and truely, for ſith theſe men bee ſound and ſtronge, and will notwithſtanding bee ydle, I beleeue to keepe them, (cheefely with euill condici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) is no great charitie, and hauinge no ſeruice at their handes, I cannot maintaine reaſonably, that they are profitable.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>I am very glad, that you are perſwaded to ſee, that many thinges vſed in the Country, &amp; accomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted godly, bee not euer as they ſeeme.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>In deede, I yeelde vnto you, and had I conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered ſo much a dozen yeares ſince, it would haue ſaued mee two thouſande poundes of victuals, that theſe good fellowes haue deuoured: But tell mee touching my next allegation, honour and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>To that I ſay, that your honor or worſhip, reſteth not either in your Countrey aboade, or keeping of many ſeruaunts, but rather in your owne vertue. For though wiſe men for curteſy, &amp; fooles through ſimplicitie, doo ſalute you with reuerence, yet muſt you not thinke your ſelfe the more honorable, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe you be in deede vertuous: I meane wiſe, va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyaunt, iuſt, temperate, liberall, affable, modeſt, and in ſomme, indued with all ſortes (or at the
<pb facs="tcp:183879:26" rendition="simple:additions"/> leaſt wiſe) with ſome vertuous morrall and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable condicious, wherby you may be known, and at occaſions vſed, in the ſeruice of our Prince and Country, either Martially or Ciuilly: for thoſe bee occupations of all nobility, in which word is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded all ſortes of Gentlemen, aſwell thoſe that beare greateſt Tytles, as they that haue leſſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>I finde it far otherwiſe then you ſay, for albeit a man bee (as few are) in poſſeſſion of all theſe vertues, which (you ſay) doth onely make men honourable: yet if hee bee no Houſeholder, nor keeper of ſeruaunts, you ſee that in his Countrey, neither the neighbours will loue him, nor y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people do him reuerence.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>I did not, nor will not ſpeake agaynſt houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdinge, nor yet haue I inuayed agaynſt keping of honeſt and neceſſary ſeruauntes: but againſt the ſuperfluitie in either: For I confeſſe that hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitallity, bee it in Towne or Country, is good and godly, and alſo a teſtimony of liberality, which is a great vertue, and very commendable. But therwith bee content that I tell you, that though all good houſekeepers bee the more honourable, yet euery one that can not, or doth not kepe houſe, or ſeruaunt, muſt therfore bee diſdained or holden vile.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>I know not what ye mean by diſdain or vilety, but I am ſure, be a man neuer ſo vertuous, vnles hee be a houſekeper, no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wil in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> country reſort vnto
<pb facs="tcp:183879:27"/> him, or if hee walke in the Cittie without ſeruants attending on him, no man wil put off his cap or do him reuerence: how can then ſuch a man bee hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, yes ſyr, as much (or perhaps) a great deale more, then hee that ſpendes a thouſand poundes a yeare in his houſe, or hath in the Towne twenty men to follow him. For though a vertuous man doth walke alone for lacke of abillity and ritches, yet (if hee bee knowen) hee ſhalbe honored: though (for want of ſeruaunts) hee ſeemeth not to euery one, that hee is honorable, becauſe it is the vertue of minde, and not the guifts of fortune, that honor is due vnto.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>Mee thinkes, you ſpeake wel: and I muſt needs allow that a vertuous man (though hee bee poore) deſerueth to bee reſpected, and honored: yet expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience teacheth the contrary, that men of Title and wealth, are euer honored, and the poorer ſorte (though full fraught with vertue) doo paſſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reputation: As for example, when we Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of the Countrey doo reaſon, (as many times wee doo) of Noble men, Knightes, and all other degrees, comparinge ſome one to an other of the ſame callinge: we accompt him more or leſſe hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable or worſhipfull, as hee is more or leſſe landed or wealthy.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>I doo not vnderſtand you, I pray you tell mee, as how you make your compariſon.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:183879:27"/>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>If there bee two Lordes in our Countrey, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one hath twenty hundreth pounds in reuenue, and the other but fifteene, wee ſay, hee that hath the more liuinge is the more honourable Lorde. And likewiſe, if two Knightes, the one hauinge a thouſand pounde rent, the other not half ſo much, wee ſay they bee both men of worſhippe, but not worſhipfull alike, but the one more, the other leſſe: And ſo from degree to degree, wee make our eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation: Alſo you ſhall ſee it as a rule, taken and followed amonge Gentlemen, that hee that hath leſſe lyuinge, giueth place to him that hath more: though for byrth and vertue, hee much better. The ſame guiſe their good wiues vſe in the Countrey: for a ritch Lawyers wife, or the wife of a luſtye younge Francklin, that is lately become a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman <hi>(Gra mercé, Monſer le Harrault)</hi> will make no ceremony I warrant you to ſit downe and take place before any poore Gentlewoman, bee ſhee ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo vertuous, wel borne or married to a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in deede, of a good race, vnleſſe hee hap to haue either authority in the Countrey, or good plenty of lyuinge.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>I doo now vnderſtand well, how the worlde walketh, and am ſorry for it, ſithe that which is without the man ſhould more honour him, then that is within him. This eſtimacion I muſt (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding that the multitude do allow it) vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reiecte as falſe and vile.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>And why? will you oppoſe your ſelf to the opinion
<pb facs="tcp:183879:28"/> of ſo many: I dare ſay, if you come into the country and aſke of this matter, I warrant you they will ſay (without exception) the wealthier man, is the more honeſt man: and the greater landed Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, the better man of worſhip.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Then by that reaſon, my <hi>Lorde Mayors</hi> Horſe, is a worthier beaſt, then <hi>Maiſter Recorders</hi> Moyle, becauſe hee carrieth a ritcher burden: For that in your accompt, thinges without vs bee thoſe that honour the perſon. But this folly and falſe iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in honour, commeth of ignorance, and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance proceedeth from your manner of life in the Country, where in deede, you neuer attende to know what doth become you, but what may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritch you, wherin you are far ſhort of the Lawyer, and Ploughman, the one hauing a trade to ketch coyne, by his counſell and crafte, the other by his labour and lucke. You in the meane ſeaſon (though in troth, attentiue enough to heare of profit:) yet mixting your thirfty deſire with mirth and ſolace, as banking, and hunting, can neuer attaine to that wealth, which they do, and yet you will yeeld them honour. Certainly, if you had beene traded vp in the Court or Towne, you would caſt an other ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt of this matter, and bee not ſo barely minded as to way the worth of men, by the rente of their landes or the money in their purſes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>I did not ſay, that this was my iudgement, but the opinion almoſt vniuerſall, for if one man in the Countrey do hold your minde, I dare ſay you ſhal finde an hundreth to incounter him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:183879:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>It may ſo bee (cheefely in this corrupt age,) but for my parte, though twiſe a hundreth men did en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter my iudgement, I care not, for I am ſure there is not one wiſe man among two hundreth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>Well, I am content to yeelde rather to reaſon then the multitude, and beleeue with you, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> men are more or leſſe honourable, as they are more or leſſe vertuous, not meaſuring them (as the multy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude doth) as they are layed in Subſedy bookes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>I thanke you ſyr, for dooing mee ſuch fauour, as to concurre with mee in opinion. I pray you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede in the reſt of your countrey commendacions.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>Then muſt I ſpeake of the holſomneſſe of our dwellinges, which without contradiction is much more, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your aboad in Citties, Court, or townes where the ayre is commonly ſtraught, &amp; the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of people great: which two thinges muſt needes breede contagion and ſicknes, there wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth alſo commodity for exerciſe, which is a thinge very neceſſary to maintaine health, we may at our willes walke, &amp; ronne, hauke, and hunt, our feelds beeing ſpacious, and our game plentifull. All which thinges you want in Court &amp; Cittie, or with great difficulty you haue them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Euery commodity beareth about it, ſome diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodity: yet if I luſt to reaſon, ſo needles a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleme, I could ſay, that as Courtes and Cities, by reaſon of the concourſe of people become oft times
<pb facs="tcp:183879:29"/> vnpleaſauntly aired, yet the ſight is of more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance and worthier conſideracion. For it may bee that a perticuler houſe in the country, (as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly all olde buildinges were) bee as low, and vnholſomly placed, as any Cittie, for hereof was greater aduiſe in ſytinge it. Alſo therin are great prouiſions to preuent corruption and ſicknes: the people alſo beeing therin, are more neate and ciuill then they bin in the countrey: For clenlynes is a ſpeciall preſeruatiue againſt infection, yea, if you did, or could know the whole number of people that did inhabit London, or any other cittie, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paringe them with as many of the Countrey, and marke how many died weekly of either, you ſhould commonly ſee the thing would fall out indifferent, though at ſome one time died more Citizens, yet at ſome other you ſhould finde, as great plagues and ſickneſſe, among the Maſſe of your countrey folke. And for your exerciſes (which I confeſſe are honeſt and good,) I will ſpeake of them here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after when you hap, (as you haue promiſed) to praiſe the pleaſure of your countrey dwelling: Let it then ſuffiſe, that touchinge the good or euill ayre and holeſomnes, or vnholeſomnes of our diuerſe dwellinges, I refer you to the ſighte of the places, and leaue them to your wiſedome without compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe. Wee liue here, till wee can no longer, and you till you die: ſome are very healthy, and ſome euer ſickly: ſome haue much of the one, and ſome of the other. Euery man to his fortune.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>Then ſyr, let that bee, as bee may, for I finde in euery ayre, ſome liue longe, &amp; ſome leſſe, though
<pb facs="tcp:183879:29" rendition="simple:additions"/> few ſo longe as they would: but now let vs com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon of our quiet.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>With all good will, I am content to heare you, ſay what you luſt, for it will pleaſe mee much, to know of your quiet life.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>Vnderſtand you (good <hi>Maiſter Vallentine</hi>) that our houſes bee, (or at the leaſte) the moſt auncient of them, ſited in places remote, and far from any Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, Burrough, (or almoſt) Village, wherby wee want thoſe noyſome noyſes of cryinge and carria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, which neceſſarily the Citizens muſt abide. Our gates bee not euery handwhile knocked, for either they are all day open, or that our Porters bee ſtill preſent to let men in and out, wee are not much troubled with ſendinge too and fro, for our prouiſions: becauſe euery Gentleman, if hee bee a man of any reaſonable lands, and forecaſt, he hath about home, vpon his owne demeanes, all ſorts of victuall for horſe and man, and likewiſe fewel: So as in concluſion, I tell you hee needeth not to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet himſelfe, either in ſence or wit, vnleſſe it bee ſome one ambitious Gentleman amonge many, who (becauſe he would ſeeme more venorable the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the reſt) wilbe ritchly apparrelled, and fill his Sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler with Wines of ſundry ſortes, which prouiſion in deed wee haue not without ſending to London, or ſome great Cittie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>I perceaue (as partly I did before) that your houſes bee far from company, which in the reſpect you haue ſpoken, are the more quiet, and yet mee
<pb facs="tcp:183879:30"/> thinkes, I would not want the comforte of neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured for the quiet you haue tolde vs, which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe may bee enough: And wheras you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leage that your prouiſions at hande doth acquire you of trouble, which wee haue in the town, therin I iudge you deceaue your ſelfe. For albeit corne groweth on your owne demeane, and your wood likewiſe, alſo your cattell and all countrey foode: yet dare I warrant you before ſuch time as the ſame prouiſions be fit for your vſe (I meane, your Lande manured, your corne reaped, your woods cut downe, &amp; all thinges ready, and brought home as they muſt bee: your trouble and diſquiet wilbe much more then ours, that ſende twiſe a day from our houſe to the Market in the towne where wee dwell.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>In deede I had forgotten, that wee haue much adoo in ſeed ſeaſon, to ſet forth our Plowes, in har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt to reape our corne, and towards winter to lay in our fewell: But all theſe thinges yet wee haue without money, which you haue not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Without money? But ſyr by your fauour, not without coſt, and other whiles wee haue them bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter cheape then you, though they growe on your owne ground, as I will hereafter perſwade when I ſhall anſwere you, touchinge the profite of the Countrey, which is one of your allegations,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>Then do I longe much to heare, yet let mee tel you one touch more of our quiet, which is our auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, for a number of vs bee Iuſtices, ſome of
<pb facs="tcp:183879:30"/> 
                  <hi>Quoram,</hi> and many of the Peace, ſome Shreeues ſome Surueyors, ſome Eſchetors, ſome Feoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and ſuch like, others alſo, though in no office, yet beeinge diſcended of wealthy and worſhipfull houſes, are much reſpected, worſhipped and feared of the people: But if the beſt of theſe remayned in Court (without office there) or in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Citty or town, the meaneſt Marchaunt, or ſyllieſt Shoemaker, woulde ſcantly reſpecte vs, and none at all feare vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Nor wee them: and yet ſhall I ſpeake plainely, I had rather bee worſhipped or reſpected of one ciuil or wiſe man (ſuch as liue in Courts or towns) then of one hundreth Countrey loutes, that either doo ſalute you for flattery, or honour you ignorant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: And lothe would I bee, to finde you ſo groſſe, as to thinke that among twiſe tenne of thoſe plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyall ſortes, there bee two of iudgement enough to know what honour is due to one, more then to an other.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>And why ſo ſyr? yes I warrant you that they vnderſtand, what Noble man or Gentleman doo dwell neare them, and what honour is due to ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: Neyther are they ſo ignorant, or vnciuil, but if they hap to meet any ſuch well apparrelled per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, in his worſhipfull garmentes, or with a fayre cheyne about his necke, the countrey lowtes (as you terme them) can ſo much good manner, as to put off their hats, and if the Gentleman be braue in deede, they will alſo doo him other reuerence.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:183879:31"/>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Not ſo, but I thinke verely they will often do reuerence to the Gentlemans cheyne, or his braue coate, which curteſie men of iudgement do not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, for they would be honoured for them ſelues and their vertue, and though no man doth commit Idolitry to their cheynes, or garmentes they force litle: which error I haue ſeen not only co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to commit, but (by your leaue,) many of your worſhipfull inhabitantes, who by reaſon, you are continually abydinge in the Countrey, you know neither the perſons of the Nobillity, nor yet the very Magiſtrates that gouerne. Wherby (when happely ye bee called before them,) you know nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther what difference to make, either of their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons or dignities. The like ſimplicity I haue ſeen in your Wiues: and yet in them more excuſeable, (becauſe they may not modeſtly without your leaues, ſee ſo much of the world:) who when they come to Court, do neither know the gentlewomen from the Ladyes, nor ſcantly the Queene her ſelf. What Gentleman or Gentlewoman would not be aſhamed of ſuch ignoraunce, and wiſheth not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that he had ſpent twiſe two hundreth pounds then to ſhew him ſelfe to bee ſuch a one as I haue tolde you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>In very deede, <hi>(Maiſter Vallentine,)</hi> it is meete for euery Gentleman to know, the perſon of his Prince: and likewiſe of the Magiſtrates, (or at the leaſt, of the moſt of them) and ſurely ſuch know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is not gotten without comminge to Court, or places where they reſort: Notwithſtanding if
<pb facs="tcp:183879:31"/> all Gentlemen ſhould follow the Court or dwel in London, how ſhould the countrey bee gouerned? For without Iuſtices of Peace and officers there, the people would be out of order, and the Princes ſeruice muſt needs bee neglected.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Although I take vpon mee to remember Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, of their groſſe ignorance and lacke of ciuility, yet is not my intent to traine them all their whole liues, out of their countrey, neyther would I wiſh them, (cheefely Officers, &amp; miniſters of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in Iuſtice) to remaine alwaies: either in court or Cittie: But to reſort thither at ſuch age &amp; times, as hee is either not imploied, or not needed, which if hee did (I am moſt aſſured) his ſeruice woulde prooue the more worth, and him ſelf a great deale the more ciuill: If it pleaſeth you to conſider that if any important ſeruice bee co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted to the Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of any Shier, you ſhall ſee the ſame (or the cheefe truſt therof) allotted to men knowen to the Prince or the Councell, and not to others. And if after the ſayd ſeruice bee performed and any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port therof muſt bee made, if a man do come to do that office (beeing before knowen to the Prince or Magiſtrates, you ſhal finde hee ſhalbe heard with more reſpecte, and diſpatched with more ſpeede, then if any other vnknowen, or vnſkilfull perſon had beene preſented vnto them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>No doubt of that, but would you haue all Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men thus finely brought vp, and that there ſhould no Iuſtices of Peace remayne in the Countrey, mee thinkes that were exceeding ſtrange?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:183879:32"/>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>I did wiſh indeed, that all Gentlemen were wel brought vp, and reſorters to Court or Cittie, yet I ſaide not that they ſhould euer abandon the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, cheefely thoſe that are imploied there.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>Then it ſeemeth that you would haue all the reſt to bee Courtiers and Townes men, how ſhould any of them then aſpire to the offices of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, when there they are not abidinge.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>My meaning is not to entice them all to Court, or to Cittie from their naturall ſhier: But that ſuch (as would not doo them ſelues that great good) that at the leaſt they would ſome times, &amp; cheefely in their youth, abide in their cheefe towne or cittie of their countrey, where they may conuerſe with a people more ciuill, then the poore villaines, and bee notwithſtanding at hand to take office (if it be layed on them:) Alſo if they bee in office already, they dwell there fitly enough to exerciſe the ſame. But by this you haue ſaide, it ſeemeth you are, or faine would bee an Officer in your countrey.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>Nay not ſo ſyr, but yet if it bee layed vpon mee, I muſt not refuſe to ſerue my Prince.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>I warrant you ſyr, if you bee no better acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in Court then you ſeeme, nor no better learned then I, you ſhall neuer bee troubled with office, vnleſſe ſome freend of yours doo recommend you, for ſo obſcure education as you ſpeake, will ſlowly prefer you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:183879:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>I confeſſe our preferment is ſlow, and yours (bee it ſpoken with patience) is not ouer ſwift. For if you marke well it is much better to ſmell of the law, then of the Launce.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>By my fay ſyr, you haue hit mee home, for truely I wiſh that thoſe ſauours did yeeld thrift alike. But how happy are you, for whom fortune hath ſo well prouided, as you neede neither to taſte the paines of the one, nor the perrill of the other. But <hi>Baſta.</hi> Let vs returne to the matter, &amp; tell mee how ye are perſwaded of my ſpech touching your quiet.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>Exceedingly well: And muſt acknowledge that in manuringe our owne groundes, wee offer our ſelues much diſquiet and care, not becomminge a Gentleman. Alſo in conſideration of our ſtrangnes to the Court, wee are made the leſſe meete for go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, &amp; not to know the perſon of our Prince is a thinge that amazeth a Gentleman much. I yeelde therfore vnto your reaſons, and the rather becauſe you will neither binde vs continually to Court, nor London: But that wee may both viſit our owne countrey houſes, and yee make cheefe abode in our ſhier townes, as places to keepe vs in that ciuilitie, is behoouefull.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>You vnderſtande mee right, and you ſhall by your dwellinge in thoſe Townes, much enritche the people, that they thereby enhabled maye make their buyldinges the more beautifull and commodious, ſo that in one acte you woorke
<pb facs="tcp:183879:33"/> two good effectes, which are to make your ſelues ciuill, and enritch the townes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>But how ſay you to our pleaſures and pleaſant exerciſes of the countrey? for that was the next I promiſed to praiſe. I truſt you will allow of them, and commend your owne coldly, for I thinke they be colde enough in deede.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Well ſyr, I perceaue you haue a colde conceit of of our Courtly pleaſures, but what of that: tel vs yours I pray you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>Wee haue in troth ſo great ſtore of them, as there is no time of the yeare, no houre of the day, nor no weather, but wee haue a paſtime to entertaine vs with.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>As how? for Gods ſake, ſay on.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>In the ſpring time (and cheefely in Lent) wee fiſh the Carpe, the Pike, the Breame, the Roche, and the Yeele, as good meates in the eatinge, as good ſportes in the ketching. In ſommer we dare the Larke with Hobbies, and ketch them with day Nettes. In harueſt when corne is downe, our Sparkaukes bee ready to kill the Partridge, the Quayle, and Rayle. In winter wee hauke the Heron, the Feaſant, the Ducke, the Teale: And in breefe, all ſortes of volary. The like pleaſures wee can ſhew you vpon the ground, (for you muſt conceaue that all theſe fowles doo fly,) and bee it your will to hunt with your eye or eare, wee are
<pb facs="tcp:183879:33" rendition="simple:additions"/> ready for you as if you pleaſe to ſee with the eye, wee courſe the Stagge, the Bucke, the Roa, the Doa, the Hare, the Foxe, and the Badger: Or if you had rather haue ſome <hi>Muſicke</hi> to content your care, out goes our dogges, our houndes (I ſhould haue ſaide) with them wee make a heauenly noiſe or cry, that would make a dead man reuiue, and run on foote to heare it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>But by your leaue, if you wiſht your owne good father, whoſe Heire you are, would riſe from death to life, you had rather neuer heare hound, then trouble his reſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>Very well ſyr, you thinke I would bee lothe to trace my Fathers new ſteppes vpon his olde land, I ſpeake like a hunter, and to tell you plainely, as I neuer deſired his death: So were it no reaſon I ſhould put him to paines, of receauing his arre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage of rents, which I haue ſpent theſe half dozen yeares paſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Much good may it doo you, and let him reſt, <hi>(God giue him reſt:)</hi> But tell mee if all theſe plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, wherof you tolde, bee they vſed by day or night, in faire weather, or fowle?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>In good ſooth <hi>(Maiſter Vallentine)</hi> either you are wonderouſly pleaſaunt, and diſpoſed, or els very ignorant in Gentlemens quallities, that will aſke me theſe vain queſtions: For euery man knoweth that the day time is fitteſt for all ſportes, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the faire weather.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:183879:34"/>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Ah ſyr, I pray you pardon mee, for I confeſſe I am vnſkilfull, yet vnleſſe I bee much deceaued, I haue hard hounds barke by night, &amp; haue ſeene foulers ketch Woodcockes in colde weather.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>In deede it may bee, you haue hard ſumtimes hounds yorne, (for ſo you ought to terme it) by night, and I ſuppoſe the winter weather and hard, is fitteſt for ketching of Woodcockes in deede.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Well, I am glad, you know therby I haue hard, and ſeene ſumwhat worthy a Gentleman: I pray you now tell vs your paſtimes, deſtined for fowle weather, &amp; how many be of them, beſides ketching of Woodcockes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>I aſſure you many, and thoſe diuerſe (in which I will include our exerciſes alſo: but becauſe you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund of our fowle wether paſtimes, I wil ſpeake of them firſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>You are full of memory &amp; order, I pray you ſay on.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent</speaker>
               <p>In fowle weather, we ſend for ſome honeſt neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, if happely wee bee with our wiues alone at home (as ſeldome we are) and with them we play at Dice, and Cardes, ſorting our ſelues accordinge to the number of Players, and their ſkill, ſome to Ticktacke, ſome Lurche, ſome to Iriſh game, or Dublets: Other ſit cloſe to the Cardes, at Poſt &amp; Paire, at Ruffe, or Colcheſter Trumpe, at Mack or Maw: yea, there are ſome euer ſo freſh game<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters,
<pb facs="tcp:183879:34"/> as wil bare you co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany at Nouem Quinque, at Faring, Trey trip, or one &amp; thirty, for I warrant you, we haue right good fellowes in the countrey, ſumtimes alſo (for ſhift of ſports, you know is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectable) we fall to ſlide thrifte, to Penny prick, &amp; in winter nights, we vſe certaine Chriſtmas games very propper, &amp; of much agilitie, wee want not alſo pleaſant mad headed knaues, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> bee properly lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and will reade in diuerſe pleaſant bookes, and good Authors: As <hi>Sir Guy</hi> of <hi>VVarwicke,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> foure <hi>Sonnes</hi> of <hi>Amon,</hi> the <hi>Ship</hi> of <hi>Fooles,</hi> the <hi>Budget</hi> of <hi>Demaundes,</hi> the <hi>Hundreth merry Tales,</hi> the <hi>Booke</hi> of <hi>Ryddles,</hi> and many other excellent writers, both witty and pleaſaunt. Theſe pretty and pithy mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, do ſome times recreate our mindes, cheefely after longe ſittinge, and loſſe of money. In faire weather when we haue ſtraungers, or holly daies (for els in the day time wee attend our thrift) wee exerciſe our ſelues in ſhooting at Buttes, Prickes, Roauers and Rownes: We caſt the Bar or ſledge, Leape or Run, if our ages and condicion bee fit for ſuch exerciſe, els (beeing aged) wee chat at home, and talke of <hi>Turryn,</hi> and <hi>Torny,</hi> or ſome other no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table war, wherin wee ſerued our Prince: Or if wee haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually dwelt at home, &amp; bin Iuſtices of Peace, we acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt what graue Iudges &amp; gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men we haue ſeene ſit on our Bench, &amp; with what eloquence we haue (when it was our turne) geuen the charge.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Certainly ſyr, you haue told mee of many proper pleaſures, and honeſt exerciſes: But with all let mee aſke you what Neighboures theſe compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons bee, of whom you haue tolde mee.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:183879:35"/>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>They are our honeſt neighbours, Yeomen of the Countrey, and good honeſt fellowes, dwellers there about: as Graſiers, Butchers, Farmers, Drouers, Carpenters, Carriers, Taylors, &amp; ſuch like men, very honeſt and good companions.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>And ſo I thinke, but not for you beeing a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man: For as their reſort vnto your houſe ſhal giue them occaſion to learne ſome point of ciuillity, and curteſie, ſo your conuerſinge with them will make you taſte of their bluntnes and ruſticitie, which wil very euill become a man of your calling.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>What would you then haue mee liue alone, and ſollitary? That were worſe then to bee dead.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Nay, neither, for if you did, for the moſt liue in Court or Cittie among the better ſorte, you ſhould euer finde company there, fit for your eſtate and condicion: I meane Noble and Gentlemen, (with whom if you had acquaintance) you would litle de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in this ruſtical conuerſation, and leſſe reioyce at that mirth, which (now not knowinge better) doth (as it ſeemeth) pleaſe you much.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>If theſe paſtimes bee not fit for a Gentleman, what would you haue vs to make our ſelues mery with?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>That wil I tel you hereafter, when you demaund to know the paſtimes and exerciſes of Court. In the meane time, tell on your owne tale, being now
<pb facs="tcp:183879:35" rendition="simple:additions"/> come to the laſt commodity of the Countrey which is profit.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>I thought it had beene needles for mee to haue ſaide any thinge therof, becauſe I thinke you ſee y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matter in ſuch experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, as it nedeth no diſpute.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>What meane you by that? when there is nothing (as I tolde you long ſince,) perfitly good, nor per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitly euill, onely vertue and vice except.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>All this while you flye aboue my pitch, I praye you ſpeake plainely, doo you thinke the thrifte of Noble men and Gentlemen, haunting the Court, or inhabitinge the Citties, is comparable to the good huſbandry and profit of the Country?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Yea ſurely do I, and therfore conclude not in haſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>How can it ſo bee, when the moſt part, yea in effect, all Courtiers, and towne dwelling Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men bee beggers (or at the leaſt poore in purſe) and wee of the Countrey, bee either all, or the greater number, very wealthy, or ritche enough.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>All this may bee true, and yet neither the Court or Towne is cauſe of their pouerty, nor the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey dwelling, the occaſion of your ritches.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>Well ſyr, ſith experience will not perſwade you, I will ſet downe ſome reaſons to drawe you to mine opinion. And firſt call you to memory the continuall &amp; exceſſiue charge which the Courtier,
<pb facs="tcp:183879:36"/> or Cittie dweller is at, I mean in feeding him ſelf, ſeruauntes, and famely: likewiſe how coſtly and almoſt princely hee apparrelleth him ſelfe, his wife, his children, and ſeruauntes, and all this charge goeth from the purſe, for prouiſion hath hee none: neither doth hee ſow any graine, reare any cattel, nor his wife and women ſeruaunts ſpin any cloth, &amp; though they ſo did, none I ſuppoſe of you would weare it, ſuch is your pride. On the other ſide, all the corne wee make our bread of, groweth on our demeane ground, the fleſh wee eate, is all (or the moſt parte) of our owne breeding, our garmentes alſo, or much therof, made within our houſe. Our owne Mault and water maketh our drinke: So as in concluſion, I ſay that ſith the neceſſities of mans life conſiſteth vpon theſe: I meane meate, drinke, and cloth. (All which coſt vs nothinge, or very litle, and you very much) how can you in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon conceaue, that wee ſhould bee no ritcher then you, that haunt Courts, and inhabit Citties.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>What you alleage, or the moſt therof, I thinke is true, but your concluſion falſe: For albeit your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſions be great, yet your expences beeing greater, your thrifte is like to ours, who haue ſmall prouiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and like charge.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>How can your charge bee litle, when the coſt of keepinge one man in Court, or Towne, wilbe as much, as to keepe three in the Countrey?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>And that I iudge is alſo true, but if my one man in the towne, will ſerue mee as well as your three
<pb facs="tcp:183879:36" rendition="simple:additions"/> men in the Countrey ſerue you, though that one ſpendeth mee as much as your three, I care not: for my thrift is no whit the leſſe, nor yours y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more, if of force (as in deede you muſt) keepe ſo many. For where there is (as you alleage) great Tillage, rearinge vp of Cattell, Spinninge, and Cardinge, with daily reſorte, beſides of ſtraungers, (as is commonly to Gentlemen in the Countrey,) there muſt needes bee alſo many ſeruauntes, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of people, and buſines breedeth occaſion of continuall expence of victuall: So as in effect you keepe many that doo bring you home profite, and they with others, doo ſtraight waies eate it vp, what are you then the better? but by thus much the worſe then we, that you are combred with the vnlooked for reſorte of freends and foes, and the daily feeding of many ſeruauntes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>Mee thinkes your ſpeech hath good ſence, yet becauſe it is long, I do not perfitly conceaue it, as I deſire, I pray you tell mee your reaſon breefely.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Then muſt you imagine that you haue ten loads of Haye in your Stable, and ten horſes which of force you muſt keepe. In my Stable I haue but one load, and one horſe, now will I aſke you whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther your proportion bee larger for your cattell, or mine for mee?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>They ſeeme all one, ſauinge that hee that hath the greateſt prouiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, hath alſo the greater trouble.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Then I am glad you vnderſtande: For ſuch is
<pb facs="tcp:183879:37"/> the difference, betwixt the Countrey and towne dweller, the one hath much prouiſion, and many to ſpend it, the other hath litle, and few to conſume it. So as I geſſe, all comes to one reckoninge, ſaue that the greateſt hauer, hath the leſſe quiet.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>But yet by your leaue <hi>(Maiſter Vallentine)</hi> you gay beſeen Courtiers, albeit you want prouiſion, and haue litle, yet will you alſo ſpend much. And how then?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Mary then I ſay, ſo many of vs (as indeede ſuch is the honour of the moſt) bee plaine bancke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>routes, and beggers, as you call vs, but in whom is the fault? not in the Court nor yet in the towne. But in our owne ſelues, and our owne folly: But ſuch as liue in Court or in towne orderly, &amp; ſpende within their proportion, may bee equall with you in thrifte, and in quietnes far before you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>Yet haue you not fully anſwered mee, for ſith be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides my yearly rentes, I haue three or foure hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth Acres of demeane landes, wherupon my prouiſion groweth, I accompt my houſe coſteth me nothing, when you that haue none, but liue on the penny, muſt needes ſpend without meaſure.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Why ſyr if you luſt, let out your demeanes, were it worth no rente?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>Yes that it were, for there is no Acre of it, but would yeeld mee yearely a crowne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:183879:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Then may you accompt, your prouiſion coſt you yearly foure hundreth crownes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>By my fay, you ſay troth, for if I did not eate it, I perceaue I ſhould haue it: But then how ſhould my houſe bee kept, and my neighbours loue mee?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>A great deale better now for you, &amp; other Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men diſpoſing your ſelues, (as ful yll it becommeth you) to bee Ploughmen, you haue learned what euery ſoyle is worth, and ſo after that rate, ſet out your land, wherby the poore Huſbandman or Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer payeth ſo deare for your comming, and neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borhood, as hee had rather you liued further off like a Gentleman, though for very flattery or feare when hee dineth at your Boarde, hee ſaith, hee is ſory your worſhip ſhould dwell away, when God wotteth, the poore man meaneth nothinge leſſe: For I haue learned that thoſe Tennauntes haue beſt peny worthes of their Farmes, whoſe Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lordes do leaſt know the Lande, or dwell furtheſt from it. Wherfore you deceaue your ſelfe, to thinke that your continuall dwelling in the Country, doth eaſe the poore Ploughman, ſo long as you play the Ploughman your ſelfe, or let your lande at great rente: For ſhall you not finde a number of poore Huſbandmen that almoſt ſtarue for want of lande to mannure? wherof I iudge nothinge a greater cauſe, then that Gentlemen bee become Plough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and are not contente to let the poore hier it, and liue of the rente, as their calling is, which co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetous, and clowniſhe honour they cloake vnder
<pb facs="tcp:183879:38"/> pretence of hoſpitallitie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>But if I ſhould not occupy my lande, how ſhould I know what it were worth? for this I found by experience (calling home into my handes certayne coppy houldes, let out by mine Aunceſtors) that euery Acre was twiſe ſo much worth, as the rente I receiued for it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Loe, now in erneſt you ſpeake like a worſhipfull Ploughman, not like a worthy Gentleman, for this experience, wherof you ſpeake, were better vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowen then vſed. Therfore ſome Doctors doo thinke it better not to know all thinges, then to know them: meaning (as I iudge) that euery man ſhould not bee to deepe a ſearcher in an others pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion or miſtery, leaſt led on with priuate profit he hindereth the common commoditie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent</speaker>
               <p>By this reaſon (wherin I confeſſe is good ſence) the Gentlemen of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Country that occupieth much lande with his owne Plough, and feedeth many other, letting alſo his lande wel and roundly, were aſwell ſpared, as preſent among his Tennauntes: Notwithſtanding hee keepeth good hoſpitallitie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Yea certainly, for they giue the poore men their Tennants, a meales meat twiſe a weeke worth a groate, and force him to pay a ſhillinge more then hee was wonte, before his lorde became ſo ſkilfull a huſband. Yea by your leaue alſo, if your poore Tennant preſentes you with a couple of Capons, or a Pigge, it is many times welcome, all the meat hee eateth at you Table is not ſo much worth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:183879:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>I partly conceaue now the ſubſtance of al this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe vpon profit, &amp; finde in deede that comparing the number which wee keepe in the countrey, with thoſe that you do in the Cittie, the coſt of houſehol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge commeth all to one accompt, and to confeſſe troth, I ſuppoſe there is more certenty in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of your charges then in ours. And (as I graunted before) not halfe the trouble. And ſith I am led thus far from mine olde fooliſh minde and common loue to our countrey cuſtome, to inhabite there, I will tell you of great and exceſſiue priuie charges, which wee be at in our houſes, (I meane in our houſehold ſtuffe, and cheefely linnen, for if a Gentleman haue in his houſe twenty beads, (as manye haue) and ſome a greater number, wee haue them full often occupied with ſtraungers and their ſeruaunts, who for the moſt parte bee ſo care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, or ſlouenly, as they will make quicke ſpeede to weare out not only our linnen, but alſo our hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inges, Curtaines, and Canopies of ſilke: So as within a litle time wee ſpoyle a great deale of good ſtuffe, and then forced to buy new. For as you ſee Gentlemen daily reſorte vnto common Innes, ſo do they daily reſort to Gentlemens houſes, with man and horſe, hauke and dog, till the poore Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the houſe hath al his linnen foule, al his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion eaten, &amp; his houſehold ſtuffe made vnſauery, &amp; ofttimes torne and ſpoiled. But al this notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding I acknowledge to be true, yet it greeueth mee to dwel from my owne houſe where my neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors loue me, &amp; my te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nants do feare me, yet would I faine do, as you aduiſe me were not the faſhion, and the cuſtome to the contrary.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:183879:39"/>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>By ſo ſaying, you renue an olde verſe, that beeinge a Schoole boy, I oftentimes red: <hi>Video meliora, probo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>, deteriora ſequor.</hi> But I praye you let no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge that is euil, vnfit or vnprofitable entice you to continue it, becauſe the ſame hath beene an aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient cuſtome, for I dare warrant you, that <hi>Vice is as olde,</hi> as any vertue: and yet I hope you are not ſo ſimple, as for the age (againſt all reaſon) you will allow it for good.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>In very deede, you diſcourſe ſo well, as I muſt needes confeſſe my ſelfe driuen to the wall, with playne reaſon, yet while it comes to my minde, let mee aſke you how your Wiues will bee brought to leaue their Countrey Goſſippes, with whom they haue had longe loue and familiaritie. Alſo to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge their Dayeries (which is their priuate pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite) will touch their ſtomackes neare, cheefely the thriftier ſorte, and good huſwiues? For ſome that loue not huſwiuery would eaſely bee perſwaded to the Towne, becauſe they may lye longe a bed, and weare gay garments.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Now haue you mooued a ſober doubt, and well I wot not how to anſwere therunto, vnleſſe I knew your wiues diſpoſition, for I am very lothe to offend: Notwithſtandinge becauſe wee do com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon heare priuately, and not as they doo in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament iuditially. I wil tel you my opinion touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge your wiues, I pray you heare what I ſay, but tell not them, what I ſayde: (or if you doo) ſay not from whom you had it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:183879:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>With all my hart, for I learned longe agoe, (as I remember of olde <hi>Ouid</hi> the louer) <hi>Paruus tacere labor.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Then doo I tell you flatly, that your wiues bee no leſſe, but happely more from the order of ciuili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and the life of Gentlewomen then you are your ſelues, and therfore can I lightly beleeue, they wil not bee willingly brought to leaue their Countrey goſſips, and gameſters, and more hardly to put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way their good miltch Cow: But your wiſedome muſt euer rule their couetous folly: For if you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider how vncumly a thing it is to ſee, (as I haue ſometimes ſeene, and you I am ſure often.) A Gentlewoman walkinge in the paſtures, among her Cowes, and Calues, al to be dabled with dew and dyrte, and other whiles wandering in the hot ſommer a longe mile, to finde out her hey makers, or corne reapers: So as beeing come thither, or at the leaſt before ſhee bee returned home to her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands bord, or bed, what with myre in winter, and ſweating in ſommer, ſhee is become a morſell more meete for a Mowre, or a Maſon: then a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, or a ciuill huſbande. This I know is their vſe: yea, I haue ſeene ſome of greater title then a Gentlewoman vſe this manner of toyling: And if any other Gentlewoman bee more fine or delicate (as ſhee ought to bee indeede) ſhee is miſliked a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, and called a cleane fingered girle, as though that were a great ignomy. But now ſyr, I dare promiſe that you hauinge yeelded to bee ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill your ſelfe, will no more allow of this life in your
<pb facs="tcp:183879:40"/> wiues: But remoue ſuch manners from them, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by reaſon or ouer rulinge, for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſex is not euer reaſonably.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>For my parte, I wiſh my wife were not ſo payn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full an huſwife, and yet is that no euell propertie, but a thinge very profitable. And though good huſwiues in deed, muſt neither ſhun the Sommer ſweat, nor doubt to march in the Winter myer, yet I warrant you vpon the Hollyday, or when ſhee luſt to goe into fine company, ſhee hath good gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and can weare them well and Courtly.</p>
               <p>So can alſo our Gentlemen of the Countrey, for though wee walke at home plainely apparrelled: yet when wee come to the Aſſizes, London, or any other place of aſſembly, wee will put on Courtlike garments, (and though I ſay it) ſome of vs weare them with good grace.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>I beleeue you, euen like a Conſtable in Midſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer watch. But this is no great matter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent</speaker>
               <p>Well then wee do not differ much: Let vs ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore come to concluſion, becauſe I longe to heare how men be trained, and exerciſed in Courte and Cittie, for (as it ſeemed by your ſpeeche) their man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of liues, doo much reſemble one thother.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>And ſo they doo in deed, I meane the Gentlemen, and not the Marchants and <hi>Mecanicall</hi> people, for their trade (as you can conceaue) is turned an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther waies: But I praye you ſay on, for it ſeemed, you ment to reſight in breefe the ſomme of all this ſpeech, and how well we haue by conſent reſolued.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:183879:40"/>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>That is my intent, ſo far as wit and memory will ſerue mee. But firſt let mee intreat you to tel ſumwhat of Courte, and Towne dwellinge: then ſhall you heare my minde, and concluſion of all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Verely <hi>(Maiſter Vincent,)</hi> I muſt (vnleſſe I ſhould wrong you) commend your memory a great deale, and many thankes muſt I alſo allow you, for your patience, in hearing my poore reaſon, and diſcourſe, which (as it ſeemeth) is not in vaine, but hath taken the effecte I deſired.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>Yea ſurely ſyr, and therof reſte you aſſured. I pray you now let vs forget the Countrey, and (as you promiſed,) ſay ſumwhat of the Court &amp; Cittie habitation. For I am a ſtraunger to theſe places, though your hap bee to finde mee here at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in London.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>You might thinke mee of euil manner, and leſſe curtiſie, if I refuſed to performe your reaſonable requeſt, and the rather for the honour you haue done mee, in yeelding to my reaſons.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>Then without more ceremony I praye you begin, and feele no offence, though I through ignorance doo aſke many queſtions, for mannes nature, (you wot well) is deſirous to know, cheefely thinges commendable.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Euen ſo it is. But touching my talke of the Court, and Towne habitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, although I haue at length
<pb facs="tcp:183879:41"/> prooued, that in thoſe places ought to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens cheefe aboade, yet I thinke it not neceſſary to make any new compariſon: But onely to touch ſome matters, how men do there liue, and in what ages and eſtates the Courtinge life doth become: For to take vpon mee to frame a Courtier, were preſumption, I leaue that to the <hi>Earle Baldazar,</hi> whoſe Booke tranſlated by <hi>Sir Thomas Hobby,</hi> I thinke you haue, or ought to haue reade. I wil not therfore cumber you with the educatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, for that is already ſpoken of. For whither the ſame bee in Armes or learning, it is indifferent, for (as I tolde you) the ſtate hath neede of both, and both do alike beſeeme him vnderſtande you, then that all Gentlemen inhabiting the Citties, &amp; there from their Cradle brought vp, can not bee ſo hard to bee entred into a ciuill life, as they were, beeing brought vp in the Countrey till they bee ſixteene or eyghteene yeares olde, before which time they are ſo deepely rooted in ruſticitie, as they prooue like vnto the haggard haukes, which many times are ſo wilde and indiſciplinable, as wil either neuer or with great labour bee reclaimed. The like I ſay of their liues, through ruſticall company in childe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoode, doo get them ſelues as it were an habite in loughty lokes, clowniſh ſpeech, and other vngentle manly Ieſtures, as it is a good while (yea many times neuer) that thoſe ruſticities bee leafte. But I will no more ſpeake of children: onely this I ſay that young Gentlemen, (whoſe Parentes inhabit the Citie, and are deſirous to haue their Sonnes well and vertuouſly brought vp) beſides that, they ſhalbe free from theſe Countrey conditions, they
<pb facs="tcp:183879:41"/> may, or then come to this age, bee perfitly learned in the <hi>Greeke</hi> and <hi>Lattin tongues,</hi> and other whiles in other volgare languages: alſo he may haue ſome good intrance in the ſciences <hi>Mathematicall know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges,</hi> very fitte for a <hi>Martiall</hi> man, and not vnfit for the <hi>Ciuill Officer:</hi> Whereof I infer that at this age, or ſhortly after hee is to bee iudged, wherun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hee is by nature and deſire moſt inclined.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>Wee will then for this time imagine (and for my part ſo wiſh) that all Noble and Gentlemen, did dwell in Citties, and Townes, and that therby their children ſhould not be infected with the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey conditions, but were as apte for Courte, and Ciuilitie, as you would haue them: what would you then they ſhould do, beeing come to eyghteene or twenty yeares? as you ſeeme to deſire, beeinge well entred and learned in thoſe ſtudies, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Gentleman.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>I would then (findinge the inclination of my ſonne to learninge) continue and encourage him therin, and make him (I hope) a man fit for his countrey, or at the leaſt for him ſelfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>As how? I pray you proceede: For beeing now my ſelfe perſwaded to dwell in the Cittie, &amp; haue many younge children, I would directe them the beſt I could.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>I wiſh that your ſonne, hauing paſſed the ſcholes, and ſpent ſome time in the vniuerſitie, finding him diſpoſed to learne the common lawes, you ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:183879:42"/> in any wiſe continue him, and (as I ſayd before) holde him therto as a ſtudy both neceſſary for the ſtate, and profitable for him ſelfe. Or if he rather affecteth the lawes <hi>Ciuill,</hi> or the ſcience <hi>Mathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall,</hi> I would aduiſe you (if ſuch bee your ability) to ſend him to ſtudy in the Vniuerſities of forraine Countreyes, where hee may make double profit, I meane, learne the knowledge hee ſeeketh, and alſo the language of the place.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>But I pray you, giue mee leaue to demaunde to what vſe the knowledge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawes ciuil do ſerue, for it is the law of the Realme, only (as I thinke) that bringeth in both honor, and profit.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>I deny not, but after our longe peace and quiet, (which God continue) the common lawes of this Realme, hath both aduaunced, and enritched ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, for (ſuch is the nature of men) as they neuer ceaſe one to moleſt the other, not beeinge by ſome forraine moleſtacion offended, they conuert their ambition, and couetous one agaynſt the other. Wherupon they call one the other to tryall of law, in thoſe contentions (which are many) the men of lawe, are hired and imployed, to their exceedinge profit and gayne. But touching the ciuill lawes, I ſay that is a moſt noble knowledge, beeinge the law almoſt vniuerſall to all Chriſtendome, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſuch as attaine to the knowledge therof, ſhall not onely in this lande, &amp; many other, hable them ſelues to get their owne liueload: But alſo be men moſt fit to counſell Princes, and all eſtates of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernments both in cauſes <hi>Ciuill</hi> and <hi>Martiall:</hi> For
<pb facs="tcp:183879:42" rendition="simple:additions"/> by them all differentes bee diſſided: The learned <hi>Ciuilian</hi> therfore (beſides his owne perticuler) is a man very fit, &amp; imployable in all counſels of eſtate and Ambaſſages, as hee that is ſkilfull of the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment vniuerſall. And if (as before I ſayd) his learninge begotten in forraine Countreyes, he ſhall alſo bee helped with language and ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>Surely ſyr, this is more then I euer hard, for I ſuppoſed the onely profite and reputation of this learninge had been in the <hi>Arches</hi> and <hi>Spiritual Courtes,</hi> as wee call them. But now I finde that <hi>Ciuilians,</hi> can ſerue better purpoſes, and in euery chriſtian countrey, make ſhifte to earne their owne liuinges. I pray you what ſhall we diſpoſe of thoſe young men, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> loue a Lawnce or a Sword better then either a Booke, or a long gowne?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>I thinke, I tolde you talking of the Countrey, that in my poore opinion there was no Gentilman (vnleſſe hee were witleſſe,) but might bee made fit for ſumwhat. Such therfore, as were perſons diſpoſed of Body, after the age beforeſayde, and not affected to the ſtuddie of theſe lawes, I would notwithſtanding holde them in loue of the <hi>Mathematicall Sciences,</hi> and preferre them into the ſeruice of Noble men, and Captaynes, eyther at home, or els in forraine Countryes, who haunting the warres, ſhal enſtruct theſe young fellowes, in all orders and Martiall diſcipline, wherin helped with the knowledge of the ſayde Science.
<pb facs="tcp:183879:43"/> They ſhall in ſhorte ſpare, become not onely good and obediente Souldiers: But alſo ſkilfull com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunders, and perfite Captaines. Others alſo may with daily practiſe prooue excellent in the <hi>Art of Ridinge,</hi> and others in <hi>Saylinge</hi> or <hi>Nauigation:</hi> So as the <hi>Martiall</hi> exerciſes bee diuerſe, all fitte for a Gentleman, &amp; moſt expedient for the Princes ſeruice.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>But theſe quallities bee (as I thinke) ſlow oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupations to thriue by: notwithſtanding they are full painefull and perilous, many men, yea (euery man at one time or other) haue neede of a Lawier: But a Captaine, a man of Armes, or a Souldiour (cheefly in time of peace) no man needeth. If ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a young Gentleman, beeinge of eyghteene or twenty yeares old, ſhould during fiue, ſixe, or ſeuen yeares nexte after, wholly endeuour him ſelfe in theſe diſciplines and Martiall exerciſes, and doth become in them expert, or happely excellent, retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned home into Englande, where all is peace, what vſe were there of his vertue, or who would main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne him?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>I muſt ſay thoſe ſortes of men ſeruiceable, bee not ſo well prouided for as the deſerue, &amp; I deſire. Notwithſtanding, ſith the number of Gentlemen, who apply them ſelues that wayes bee not many: I iudge beeinge men in deede of vertue and value, our Prince, (for that ſhee is both liberall, and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lourous,) would willingly afforde them maynte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce, beſides that, there are diuerſe Noble men and great Councellors, ſome very ſouldiers them
<pb facs="tcp:183879:43" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſelues, and ſome louers, as well of armes as lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that would likewiſe put their handes to helpe ſo vertuous and induſtrious a youth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>And ſo do I ſuppoſe alſo, and doo heare it daily wiſhed, that all ſortes of men imployable in the ſtate were prouided for: Notwithſtanding, ſith the vſe of theſe is but ſeldome, I ſee no ordinaunce, or ſpeciall prouiſion for them. And in deede, a man not needed, ſeemeth ſuperfluous, and may be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>You haue reaſoned wiſely, but not well, for if your Horſe ſhould no longer bee allowed Prouender, then during the time you ride him, I warrant you your iourney could not bee longe. Or if your ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunt ſhould haue wages, but for howres wherin he laboureth, then ſhould you pay him but for half the yeare, for euery night (as reaſon is) hee reſteth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>You are <hi>(Maiſter Vallentine,)</hi> very nimbly witted, and therfore will I not replye, but in that which reaſon doth maintaine. And touching our matter, Let vs preſuppoſe that ſome younge Gentleman hath in the prime of his youth diſpoſed him ſelfe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtriouſly in ſtuddy, warres, and trauell, where hee caught that knowledge or experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, that doth recommende him to the Princes ſeruice: what is the order of the life there, and wherin ſhall he exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe him ſelfe at the firſt comminge, or after ſome yeares of aboad there, and at what age may hee without offence, and in reaſon, retire him ſelfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:183879:44"/>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>You are very diſcrete and orderly in all your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunds, I would wiſh you to aſke of more ſkilfull Courtiers, for though I haue ſeene the Courtes of ſundry forraine Princes, and ſerued longe our owne Soueraigne, yet dare I not accompt my ſelf ſo perfite, as to enforme you in euery of theſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>I haue ſaide, and ſo I muſt once more ſay, that you are ouer full of reſpectes, which humor you found beyond the Mountaynes: I pray you laye by this curioſitie, and do (as you partly promiſed,) tell of the order of a Courtly life, and what exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes becommeth a Courtier in euery age, and begin at fiue and twenty yeares, or there about, for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that time, a young Gentleman may haue both ſtudied in Schooles, ſeen the warre, and trauelled Countreyes: Which three thinges, or at the leaſt one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in any wiſe I wiſh a Gentleman ſhould doo, to make him worthy of a Princes ſeruice.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Such a man, beeinge retained to the Prince, his beſt meane to aduauncement (as I thinke) is to excell, (if poſſible hee may) in that he profeſſeth, adding therunto dilligence, and fidelity in ſeruice. And if hee profeſſeth (ſpecially) armes, I would he aduentured him ſelfe, in euery honourable warre, till ſuch time as hee hath gayned the true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and reputation of a Souldier. And touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge the exerciſes of ſuch a one, duringe his aboad in Court, it ſhall well become his age and profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to handle all ſorts of armes, both on horſeback and foote, leape, daunce, runne, ride, (and if hee ſo
<pb facs="tcp:183879:44"/> like) play at all ſortes of games, ſo that hee accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panieth either his betters or equals, and that with ſuch diſcretio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as his loſſ be not at any time ſo great as to occaſion his ruyn: It will alſo ſtand wel with his condition to entertaine Ladyes, and ſerue ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſome one, whoſe vertue and priuate curteſie, doth at his hand beſt deſerue. One other thinge alſo I wiſh hee vſed, I meane that at the leaſt, one howre of euery day hee ſhould read, either in ſome notable Hiſtory, or excellent diſcourſe: For that will much exerciſe the minde, &amp; encreaſe the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>It is true, that as the ſtrength of body vnuſed, will quickly decay, ſo wil alſo the wit and memory. But I pray you tell mee when theſe luſty exerciſes will become a Gentleman, I meane, whither they bee ſeemely all his life, or but only for ſome certaine yeares?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>In this queſtion I am ſure you aunſwere your ſelfe, that they are ſeldome ſeemely, in a man of ripe age, and in olde yeares very rediculous. For if you ſhould ſee an olde Gentleman, with a white or griſly beard, take vpon him to daunce, or turney for his Miſtriſſe fauour, I ſuppoſe you would not looke on him without laughter, nor ſhee with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſdaine: yea, (ſuch is the force of cumlineſſe) as euen in thoſe that make profeſſion of dauncing, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe their yeares be fit for the vſe therof, they doo rather inſtruct others, then vſe it them ſelues. But armes becommeth a Gentleman in all ages: But yet diuerſly, for old men muſt only in earneſt vſe it.
<pb facs="tcp:183879:45"/> But young men both in earneſt &amp; ſporte, are bound to that exerciſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>Yet haue you not tolde mee how longe this lyfe wilbe ſeemely.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>I pray you preſſe mee no more with theſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunds, for I referred you to a booke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> can better enforme you. Yet ſith you ſeeke my opinion, I ſay (as in a ſorte I haue already ſayd) that theſe exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes of bodie, doo only become youth: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that age (which I ſuppoſe by the <hi>Philoſophers</hi> rule) endeth at thirty and fiue yeares doth onely grace a Gentleman in them. After that time, bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge of capaſſitie, and experience, hee is rather to be imploied in ſerious ſeruices, then left at leyſure, to entertayne Ladies, or daunce a Galliard.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>But if it happeneth hee bee not vſed in any action meete for his age and ſkill: But either through want of occaſion, freendes or fortune, let ſtand ſtill in his firſt eſtate, without either aduauncement, or imployment, beeing no longer fit for loue and dal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liance: How ſhould hee grace him ſelf in Court?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Truly (as I take it) beeing come to the declyne of his age, and drawing neare to fortye yeares, hee may without offence retire him ſelfe, and reſigne his ordinary attendance, reſortinge ſome times to ſee his Soueraigne, as a cheefe comfort. For if you conſider well, that place which requireth the perſon of a younge man, will miſbecome the ſame body beeinge in yeares: alſo, while youth and luſt
<pb facs="tcp:183879:45"/> laſted, there was hope of good: which now decaied the man becommeth not only vnfit for the place he vſed: But alſo (not preferred) looſeth the reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, wherin his vertue and expectacion did holde him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>You ſpeake like a man of experience and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as one that knoweth what is beſeeming in euery age, and eſtate. Notwithſtandinge I ſee ſome vnaduaunced, &amp; alſo vnemployed Courtiers, that dwell in their young places of ſeruice, euen to their laſt yeares.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Euen ſo in troth it is, and the occaſions thereof diuerſe. Some there are of thoſe men, very im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployable, yet therwith deepely infected with am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, and therfore will neuer leaue the Courte, clearely forgetting, that <hi>Fortune</hi> is a woman, which ſexe ſeldome preferreth folke of declyning age. Others hauinge happely committed ſome error, and therby incurred the princes offence, beeing pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent, and deſirous to recouer fauour and reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, doo notwithſtanding they know them ſelues ouer aged for their profeſſion, ſtil attend a plauſible departure: which is not quickly obtayned, for (you wot well) <hi>Ira,</hi> and <hi>Irabundia,</hi> bee ſpeedier paſſions, then are <hi>Beneuolentia</hi> and <hi>Gratia.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>The thirde ſorte, are the Children of <hi>Phao,</hi> who for want of wit, will imagine they bee euer young, neuer knowinge what becomes them, but ſtill ſtay in Courte without countenaunce, not to aſpire to any thinge, but to eate and drinke among Lords.
<pb facs="tcp:183879:46"/> For them was the <hi>Florentyne Prouerbe</hi> deuiſed, which ſaith: <hi>Chi S'inuecchia in Corte in paglia more.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, you needed not ſo far to haue fetched a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe, to apply to this purpoſe, for wee haue one of our owne: But I thanke you for yours, you teach mee betwixt times, ſome beyond ſea.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Then <hi>(Maiſter Vincent,)</hi> ſith you encounter mee with mockes, I will ſpeake no more of Court, but as I haue oft tolde, wiſh you to peruſe the booke of the Courtier.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>Yet one word more of the Court, and then ſpeake whereof you pleaſe. You ſeemed, to ſay that <hi>Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> &amp; <hi>Armes,</hi> were the true profeſſions of a gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, would you then that when hee commeth to age hee ſhould abandon one of them? I meane Armes: or be ſo diſcurteous, as no longer to loue Ladyes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>I meane nothing leſſe: But that duringe life, a Gentleman ſhould profeſſe Armes, and at occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, vſe them (as I tolde you before) in age erneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in youth, both in earneſt &amp; ſporte. Alſo I would haue all Gentlemen, euen to their dying dayes, to honour Ladyes, although to ſerue them daily in Courte and dalliance, I holde olde men farre vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meete.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent</speaker>
               <p>I am ſatiſfied, and becauſe you haue ſo ofte ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſed mee to the <hi>Earle Baldazar,</hi> I will ſpeake no
<pb facs="tcp:183879:46" rendition="simple:additions"/> more of Courte, but come home to the Cittie, which is or ought to bee our habitacion: Doth it pleaſe you to commaunde mee anye ſeruice there?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>No ſeruice good ſyr, but deſire you will commaund mee, wherin I am able.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>I know your abilitie to bee much more then I will imploye: But ſithe you ſo freely offer your ſelfe, I praye you (but not commaund you) to tell what is your order of life in the Cittie, and which bee your exerciſes, both of body and minde.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>The manner of the moſt Gentlemen, and Noble men alſo, is to houſe them ſelues (if poſſible they may) in the Subburbes of the Cittie, becauſe moſte commonly the ayre there beeinge ſomewhat at large, the place is healthy, and through the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce from the bodye of the Towne, the noyſe not much: and ſo conſequently quiet. Alſo for commoditie wee finde many lodginges, both ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and roomethy, with Gardaines, and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chardes very delectable. So as with good go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, wee haue as litle cauſe to feare infecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on there, as in the verye Countrey: our water is excellente, and much better then you haue anye, our ground and feeldes moſt pleaſaunte, our fier equall with yours. This much touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge the ſite of our Towne dwellinge and the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:183879:47"/>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>Then my deſire is to know, how you be furniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed of al ſortes of prouiſion: as fleſh and fiſh, beere and bread, wood and coale, hay and oates, with euery other thing needfull, either for your ordinary expences, or for feaſtinge your freendes at occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>All theſe thinges wee haue with leſſe labour then you of the Countrey, where the ſame doth grow: For either it is brought to our very Gates, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered vs, or els in the Market, hard at hand, wee may buy it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>But ſo dearely, as euery penny worth of prouiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the Countrey, is worth three of yours.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>That may hap ſo to bee, and yet (as I tolde you already) I may better afforde a penny for three Egges in the Cittie, then for nine in the Country.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>And how can that bee, is not nine more then three, and will goe further?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Yes truly, but ſithe a penny in Egges wil ſerue the turne, for my few I keepe in the Cittie: And your penny though it bringeth you more plenty, yet ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge you haue ſo much people, as will deuoure it, commeth not the matter to one reckoninge? ſaue that the aduauntage is ours, that in roſtinge our three Egges is not ſo great troubles as yours, in roſting of nine.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:183879:47" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>Certainely <hi>(Maiſter Vallentine,)</hi> you are an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent <hi>Arithmetrition</hi> among egges: But I pray you tell mee how ſhal our children bee brought vp, and where ſhall wee haue Scoolemaiſters to teache them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>A great number of better then any <hi>Sir Iohn</hi> of the Countrey, who moſt commonly teacheth your children, that him ſelfe knoweth not, and yet either becauſe you are lothe your Babes ſhould be ſet far from your ſleeues, or that there you may haue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> taught beſt cheape, you will in no wiſe ſeeke out a ſkilfull Tutor in deede. But when you ſhal inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite the Cittie, you haue there choice of excellent Maiſters, not only for the <hi>Grammer,</hi> and ſuch boy ſtudies, but alſo in all ſortes of learning.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>That is a very good thinge, and an excellent commodity. Now I deſire you to inſtructe mee, what repare will bee to our houſes, and how wee are to entertaine them, for I am ignoraunt in all, becauſe I neuer dwelt in the Cittie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Of my former ſpeeche, comparing the Country cuſtome with ours, you might haue gathered, that vnoccaſioned, or not contryued, no man will reſort vnto your Town houſe, except he be your brother, your ſonne, or ſome dere frend, whom you accompt as your ſelfe, els none without occaſion, which happening, they that ſeke you are ſo reſpectiue, as neither at the howre of dinner or ſupper, they will looke you, if their buſines doth not very much vrge
<pb facs="tcp:183879:48"/> them. And if happely you do inuite any, of what condition ſoeuer hee bee, his ſeruauntes doo not charge you, no nor trouble you, for they retire, till ſuch time as their Maiſter haue dined, of what de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree or title ſo euer is ſayd Lorde or Maiſter bee. So as the greateſt Lord ſhal no more peſter your Hall, or diſorder your prouiſion, then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leaſt gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, or meaneſt freend, (except it) bee that for one meale, you will to honour the great gueſt make your fare the better.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>That is a great ſauing to my purſe, and ſparing mee from trouble: In Country the cuſtome is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, the charge of our Halles is more then our owne Table, and the trouble to ſerue the ſeruants exceeding. But when wee haue no company but by theſe happes, wee ſhalbe (I ſuppoſe) very ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Euen ſo much as pleaſeth your ſelfe, for when you luſt to tarry alone, no man will preſſe you: if you wilbe accompanied, a ſmall conuitation will traine freendes vnto you, and theſe men of more ciuilitie, wiſedome, and worth, then your rude Countrey Gentlemen, or ruſticall Neighboures. If you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in graue men &amp; ſober, you ſhal eaſely acquaint your ſelfe with ſuch. If you pleaſure in myrth and pleaſant companions, they are at hand. If you like of learned men, there are they found. If you wil hauke or hunt, there are Faukners &amp; hunters enough. If you will ride, there are horſemen. And to bee ſhorte, you ſhall neuer lacke company fit for your honour, age, and deſire.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:183879:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>I am very glad of thoſe newes, for wee Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey Gentlemen loue not to eate, nor dwell alone: But yet mee thinke I ſhall hazard my health: not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtandinge, if my body bee diſeaſed (as it may bee, wherſoeuer I dwell) wee may haue (I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe) plenty of Phiſitions to cure vs. The wante of which men is cauſe that in the Countrey, many do I think daily periſh, whoſe liues might by their ſkill bee preſerued.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Yea certainly ſyr, many in deede for want of good medecines doo no doubt miſcarry: And euen in mine own experience I haue knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a Gentleman or two, that were driuen to die, for want of a poore Surgion, or a Barbor to let them blood.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>The more is the pitty. Now hauing hard what ſite I ſhall haue for my towne habitation, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe how I may be accompanied, I deſire to know with what matters I ſhall entertaine my minde, and exerciſe my body.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>I haue tolde you often, and euer will tell you, that the cheefe and pricnipall ſtudies, and delight of a Gentleman, muſt bee learninge and Armes: And therfore ſuch as haue ciuilly brought vp, do ſeldom muſe on other matters. For though they refuſe not for company &amp; conuerſation to hauke &amp; hunte, fiſh and fowle, Bowle or coyte, or any other honeſt paſtime, yet is our moſt continuall exerciſe eyther ſtudie or ridinge of great and ſeruiceable horſes, with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one we entertaine our mindes, with the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we exerciſe our bodies, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> with great delight
<pb facs="tcp:183879:49"/> Are not theſe occupations to much more purpoſe then either hauking or huntinge, or any other paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time which you Countrey Gentlemen do vſe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>In reſpect of the common wealth, I ſuppoſe they are to better purpoſe, and yet are they coſtly: For the buyinge of many bookes, and hieringe of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men to inſtruct you, is a thinge (as I take it) very chargeable. Likewiſe to maintaine two or three ſeruiceable horſes, with good feedinge and keeping, will prooue exceeding coſtly.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>You ſay truely, and yet lay by your haukes, and your dogges with their keepers, and ſuch charges as are incidente to thoſe paſtimes, then ſhall you finde that the practiſe of learninge and armes, is not more coſtly then theſe, and to dyceing and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge not comperable. You ſhall alſo conſider, that for thoſe Noble or Gentlemen that bee not bound to attendaunce to follow Court, but at their owne willes, may make prouiſion in the Cittie, and kepe their horſes there, it is a matter of ſupportable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence. And many Gentlemen there are, that ſpend yearly ſo much hay and corne, vpon huntinge and haukinge Iades, as would maintayne halfe a do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen able horſes to ſerue their Prince.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>But would you haue euery Gentleman to kepe ſeruiceable horſes, euen thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> liue to themſelues, and receaue no pay of the Prince, either in war or Court?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Yea ſurely ſyr, euery Gentleman of abillity ought
<pb facs="tcp:183879:49" rendition="simple:additions"/> to doo it, for vnleſſe hee be at all times well armed and horſed, I holde him vnworthy the name of a Gentleman, yea, though hee weareth the longe Roabe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>Then will you put our Gentlemen to double charges, I meane to keepe their haukinge nags, and their horſes of ſeruice alſo.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>I will not wiſh them to that. For I deſire onely to ſee them furniſhed like Gentlemen, not like Faulkners: if there were fewer haukes, and more horſes, I ſuppoſe it were better for the ſtate, and more worſhip for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Gentlemen. Alſo (if you marke it well) it is (beſides the neceſſity,) a better and more commendable ſight, to ſee a Gentleman ride with three fayre horſes, then fifteene of thoſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumly Curtalles.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>In that I muſt alſo concurre with you in opinion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Yea, I am ſure you will, and ſo wil euery other man in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there is either iudgement or courage. And if you were in ſome Countries, where gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men doo in deede liue a ciuill life: You ſhould daily ſee them ſo wel mounted, as would greatly delight you. And ſo great is there the deſire of knowledge in Chiualry, and the vſe of armes, as in ſundry Citties they haue by conſente, erected a pay and pention, for men expert to teach them theſe know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges: So as what with their inſtructions, and their owne exerciſe, many become cunninge, and ſome very excellent. The like prouiſions they haue
<pb facs="tcp:183879:50"/> deuiſed, for the knowledge of Philoſophy, and the <hi>Mathematicall Sciences,</hi> entertaining men excellent in them, to read publikely, who for their paines do receaue good reward, euen by the only bounty and beneuolence of Noble and Gentlemen, ſtudious of honour and vertue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>How commeth this currage and noble deſire of knowledge into thoſe people, more then vnto vs?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>I dare not take vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mee to iudge, but (as I geſſe) the want of knowledge what honour is, muſt bee the principall occaſion of our want of deſire to excel both in learninge and Armes: Yea, in my poore minde, becauſe we dwel in remote place, one gentil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man far from other, ſo as the better cannot inform the worſe: there is no meane made to enſtruct the ignorant, but euery one diſpoſeth him ſelfe almoſt as a poore Ploughman, making profit and riches the markes of all his indeuor.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>Then it ſeemeth, that the Cittie, the Court, and other places of aſſembly, (I meane of Nobility) doth occaſion men to learne the cuſtomes of curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy, and pointes of honour?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>No doubt therof, for euen experience doth prooue, that ſo it is, for if you happen into the company of two Gentlemen, (though in wit and capacity alike) the one brought vp in the Countrey, the other in Court or Cittie, you ſhall euen at the firſt ſight per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue by their ſpeeche, ieſture, and behauiour, that their educations are diuerſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:183879:50" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>And that may ſo bee, yet the behauior of both good and gentlemanly enough. For you ſhall finde few Gentlemen of the Country, but they are ſumwhat learned, and many of them brought vp in ſeruice, ſo longe as they can therby know what reuerence or countenance to vſe towards all ſortes of men.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>That is but your opinion, for I will compare their good manners, or rather their euill manners vnto the ſkill of an vnſkilfull Taylor or ſhoemaker: who dwelling among the countrey people, doth exerciſe his occupation: and not beeinge there any better workeman, is holden an excellent artizan: when in deede hee is a plaine bungler, and a very ignorant dolte. Euen ſo to thoſe that neuer ſaw any ciuile men: they that weare any good garmentes, are without other conſideration, accompted braue Gentlemen, and folke of good nurture.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>Then I perceaue that euery man that can make a coate is not a Taylor, nor euery one that hath the name of a Gentleman, and goeth well appar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relled, ought bee ſo reputed: vnleſſe the one bee ſkilfull in his crafte, and the other ſeemely in his garmentes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>You take my meaning a right, and yet you muſt not thinke that theſe externall thinges, (I meane apparrell and ieſture) bee the cheefeſt ornamentes for a Gentleman. For the inwarde vertues and perfections be in troth of moſt waight, and cheefly required.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:183879:51"/>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>So haue I hard you already ſay, but few can at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to perfection, and not many draw neare vnto it. Yet I thinke you ſhal finde in the Countrey the moſt part of thoſe that beare the name of Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, that they are of capacitie ſufficient &amp; hable to talke of their ſhire wherin they dwel, as of the fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilytie or barenes therof: of hauking or huntinge, fiſhinge or fowlinge, and finally of all ſuch matter as conſerue either pleaſure or profit, wherfore I finde no want in their wittes to bee ſupplied, vnles they happely lacke the <hi>Arte of Adulation,</hi> or the ſkil of ceremonious ſpeech, which you trauellers haue brought from beyond the Seas.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Sir you may bee bolde to tell mee of all faultes: For I can willingly confeſſe, that from far, many haue fetched full euill conditions. But therwith I pray you conſider, that who ſo buyeth corne, muſt needes put ſome chaffe into his ſackes: And ſo were yee better do then bring home no corne at all. Euen ſo hee that ſeeketh to know the beſt, muſt of force, happen vpon ſome euill: both which a wiſe man knoweth how to vſe, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one to bee ſtored, the other to bee caſt away and deteſted.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>Yet haue you not tolde mee your opinion, touching our Countrey wittes and experience, neither haue you ſayde ought, how you allowe of thoſe thinges wherin wee are able to ſpeake.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>I ſay they are not euil, neither is it vngentleman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like to haue ſkill in matters of profit or pleaſure.
<pb facs="tcp:183879:51" rendition="simple:additions"/> And yet if your capacities comprehend no greater matter, you may proue fat Franklins, or faukners for a prince, or perhaps hunts for my <hi>Lord Maior:</hi> but neuer become worthy the name of Gentlemen nor the eſtimation that therto belongeth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>In deede ſyr, I remember you tolde mee that armes and learning were the only occupations of a Gentleman, and theſe are not in troth any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Notwithſtandinge you muſt vnderſtand that the moſt of vs haue gone to froole, and many haue ſeen ſome parte of the warres.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Euery boy that hath been beaten for not lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his leſſon, is not to be accompted learned, but hee that in deede hath learning, nor hee that a few dayes hath marched in armour ought be taken for a ſouldier: no more then thoſe that for one nightes ſleepe in <hi>Parnaſſus Hill,</hi> ſhould bee reputed perfite Poets.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>Truely it ſeemeth a thinge reaſonable, that ſo noble knowledges are not gotten without long la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and perſeuerance. But I pray you tell mee what imperfection you finde in the conuerſation of our Countrey Gentlemen: whom (to tel you truly) I wiſh either more lettered, or better learned in the <hi>Martiall</hi> diſcipline.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Sith you ſo require mee, I will vſe that (which you ſay is no property of a courtier) plaineſſe. And therfore I tell you, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beſides thoſe quallities you alleaged, I finde nothing els in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Countey gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men:
<pb facs="tcp:183879:52"/> &amp; the ſame not accompanied with ſome taſte of lerning or armes, I accompt as nothing worth. Touching their conuerſation, you ſhall beſides the ruſticitie of their houſes and garments, finde them full of lofty lookes, barbarous behauiour, and vndecent dooinges. As for enſample, ſome one will laugh when hee ſpeaketh an other will cough before hee telles his tale: And ſome will gape or yawne when hee giueth the hearinge. So as in deede (vnleſſe they be of better education, few doo know what cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenance to make among y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> equals, and among their betters vtterly to ſeeke. Alſo if they hap to dine at any table, either they are ſullen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſilente, or els they fall into ſpeeche of their owne Aunceſtors, their owne landes, their owne wiues or children, other ſubiect of talke yee ſhall ſeldome finde among theſe ſortes of countrey men.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>In good fayth ſyr, when I remember al mine ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, I confeſſe that ſome of them (cheefely in company) are to ſeke which way to loke: &amp; much more how to entertaine. And this I ſpeake not only of vs that dwell in the countrey, but by your leaue of many Courtiers.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>I am not ſo ſimple, (though ſimpleſt of many) but that I finde in Courte diuerſe as vnworthy the name of Courtiers, as of you that deſerue not the reputation of Gentlemen. But yet neceſſity and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion do draw vs to be of better manner, &amp; cheefly in our dooings to vſe more reſpect. And would you practiſe mine opinion, to liue ſumtimes in country, &amp; ſumtimes in cittie, yee could not chooſe but know the thrift of the one, wherof ye boaſt, and alſo the ciuility of the other.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <pb facs="tcp:183879:52" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>All men are not apt for one thing &amp; mens delights be diuerſe: for as ſome affect the ſcholes &amp; lerning, ſo others take pleaſure in huſbandry and tillage. Some haue minde to the warres, &amp; loue to wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in forraine Countryes: others are willinge to follow princes affaires, &amp; ſome are beſt content to tarry at home &amp; liue to the ſelues. How the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould al men be expert in learning &amp; armes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>I am glad you come ſo neare mee, for now wil I put ye in minde, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> long ſince I tolde you, which is, that euery gentleman vnleſſe hee were witles will proue fit for ſome action, either <hi>Martiall</hi> or <hi>Ciuill,</hi> if he doth not, the fault in his owne, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> doth not offer himſelfe to induſtry, or his fooliſh freends y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> would not comfort him to it. And ſo in concluſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I impute y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fault to <hi>Nature,</hi> but rather to <hi>Nurture.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>I had thought that nature had made euery man ſo affected as that he had been only meet, for that his freendes put him vnto, or that his Aunceſtors before him vſed and delighted.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Touching that, I will tell you how <hi>Licurgus</hi> the Law maker of <hi>Lacedemon</hi> handled the matter, to teache the people there, what education beſides nature could do in men. Hee cauſed two dogges of one lytter to be brought vp, the one he committed to a man that delighted in huntinge, and ſo vſed that whelpe: the other was foſtered by a poore villain, willing in no wiſe that dogge to doo other then eate and feede fat. Theſe two whelpes being growe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ripe age, <hi>Licurgus</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded they ſhould be brought forth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſence of many people, and with thee<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a Hare &amp; a potful of poridge, which being
<pb facs="tcp:183879:53"/> ſhewed to the dogges, and they both let looſe, the one ran after the Hare, the other made haſt to the poriſh pot. Wherby the <hi>Lacedomonians</hi> perceaued, that education &amp; not nature, made in all creatures the difference of delightes, though ſome men are more and ſome leſſe to goodnes enclined, yet euery man apt for ſomewhat, though many haue made them ſelues fit for nothing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>To ſay troth, I know many good wits, that firſt for not beeinge by freends admitted to learne, and after through an habit of ſloth, do become both vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned and very lowtes. Others both witty and curragious, yet vſed to home, and not hearing how vertuouſly ſome their equalles haue beene, are in time rather beaſtly then braue, rather effeminate then curragious.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Well, now you ſee the minde doth much, and the endeuor therof, maketh men worthy or vnworthy the name of Gentlemen, of defaultes many accuſe nature, wherof themſelues are moſt giltie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>Concerning then (of that you haue ſpoken) how the ende of the Courtier is honour, &amp; his exerciſes, Armes and learning. And that the country gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men aſpireth to ritches, exerciſed cheefly in graſing and Tulage. It muſt needes bee, that their man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and cuſtomes are alſo diuerſe. But as they bee in birth both equall, ſo ought they to haue lyke delights &amp; cuſtomes, wherfore to vnite them it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houeth that the one ſorte do confirme them ſelues to the other.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:183879:53" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Then it is meete, that the worſe do yeelde to the better, &amp; the vnexpert, to thoſe of beſt knowledge.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>So were it both wiſedome and reaſon.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>And which of thoſe men (as you thinke) liueth moſt vertuouſly, and are fitteſt for the ſtate?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>Surely ſyr, ſince I conſidered, that we muſt not liue onely for our ſelues, and our perticuler profite, I am fully perſwaded, that a gentleman vnſkilfull in Armes and vtterly vnlearned, is ſeldome found fit for any publique function, or employment. And no man denieth but that man, who is able to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne, is a perſon more worthy and neceſſary then hee that is gouerned. For <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> a Father in Philoſophy ſayth: <hi>Regens eſt dimus recto.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>I am very glad to heare you ſo ſay, for that was all I laboured you to beleeue: yet before we put ful ende to our ſpeech, let mee intreate you to tell that a good while ſince, your ſelf offered, which is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite in breefe, the ſum of all our ſpeech, wherby yee ſhal ſhew the excellency of your owne memory and alſo make theſe Gentlemen our hearers the better to carry away what hath beene ſayd.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vincent.</speaker>
               <p>Vnderſtand you then, that through your good reaſons (for which I hartely thanke you) I am brought to know that the education of a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ought bee onely in Learning and Armes, and that no Gentleman, no nor no Noble man ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:183879:54"/> withdraw or holde backe his Sonne from the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayning of theſe knowledges, which are the very true and only quallities or vertues of a gentleman as things not only beſeeming ſuch a perſon, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo for the ſeruice of a Prince or State very neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary.</p>
               <p>Secondly, you haue perſwaded that in Court or Towne, the life of a Gentleman may bee no leſſe godly and charitable, then in the Countrey: In which diſcourſe you ſet downe what ſortes of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes were ſuperfluous, and which neceſſary, both for priuate vſe, and the publike ſtate. Wherin I alſo noted, that ſuch younge men as were not borne to lande or lyuing, ſhould eyther apply them ſelues to perfection in learninge or Marchandize, either elſe to huſbandry, or ſome <hi>Mecanicall</hi> miſtery or occupacion: And not to be ſeruingmen, without other knowledge, leaſt through their Maiſters want of will to kepe them, or their lacke of ſkill to earne their owne liueloades, they may be driuen to vnlawfull life or beggery.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, in conſideration of your reaſons I gea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that true honor conſiſteth not in the admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of common people, but in the vertue of him that therwith is indued. And that the reputation which a few wiſe men do giue vnto a Gentleman, is of more worth then that of the multitude, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon is inferred, that the reſpect which is borne to any man by them of the Court and Cittie, (beeing the beſt and wiſeſt ſort) is more eſtimable then that which is borne by the common people.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, you ſeeme to allow more of many our Countrey ſportes &amp; exerciſes, then of our company
<pb facs="tcp:183879:54" rendition="simple:additions"/> in vſinge them.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, that for health and holeſome habitation the Citties, and ſome cheefe townes in England, are either better or not inferiour to the ſites of the Noble and Gentlemens houſes.</p>
               <p>Sixtly, I ſee that the Towne dwellinge doth much ſurpaſſe for quietneſſe, &amp; that the moſt parte of Gentlemens countrey houſes be frequented as honourable hoſtries.</p>
               <p>And laſt, that the Court or Cittie habitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not abuſed, is no leſſe profitable then y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> of the country, &amp; more free from trouble. <hi>Thus much of the country.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Touching the Court and Cittie, you tolde that a Gentleman ought in the prime of his youth, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour him ſelfe to become ſufficient for the ſeruice of his Prince. Which ſufficiency is attained vnto through ſtudy, trauaile, and <hi>Martiall</hi> endeuour. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forminge breefely, at what age hee ought come to Court, what his exerciſes ſhould bee there, and in what time and fortune it ſhal become him to retier him ſelfe from thence: For (as it ſeemeth,) an olde Courtier vnpreferred and vnimployed, looſeth his reputacion, and may be compared to a <hi>Non profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiens</hi> in Schoole. Concerning the reſt, you referre mee to the Booke of the Courtier.</p>
               <p>Of the Cittie, you haue ſayd ſumwhat perticulerly of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> manner and ſyte of Gentlemens houſes there and likewiſe, how they may with commodity and reaſonable coſt bee furniſhed of al ſorte of victuals and other needfull prouiſion. Alſo that there be more ſkilfull Tutors to inſtruct your children, then wee poſſible can haue in the Country.</p>
               <p>You doo alſo diſcourſe well of the manner of
<pb facs="tcp:183879:55"/> houſeholdinge and the reſorte of freendes in the towne, which ſeemeth not to be comberſome.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, it appeareth your exerciſes bee cheefely in Letters and Armes, which bee both commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable and very neceſſary.</p>
               <p>Thus much (as I thinke) is the ſomme or prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall partes of your ſpeeche, which I confeſſe to bee very reaſonable and good, and therfore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent that a Gentleman ſo brought vp, is more ciuil then any Country man can bee: Likewiſe meeteſt for gouerment, and for his priuate vertue moſte to bee regarded.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vallentine.</speaker>
               <p>Surely ſyr, you haue framed a proper <hi>Epilogue</hi> of our ſpeech. And ſithe I ſee that you both con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue aright what hath beene perſwaded, and are alſo brought to beleeue what is true, I will preſſe you no further, but bidding you moſt hartely wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come to our towne habitation, as a place fitteſt for a Gentleman. <hi>I take my leaue.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:183879:55"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:183879:56"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:183879:56"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
